<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "../../nlm/tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">10</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="index">urn:lsid:arphahub.com:pub:6BEA2F36-F41A-5C4C-8F71-33F322F204B5</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="aggregator">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0D3F4FBA-8FC4-4738-B942-05DB471A61E6</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title xml:lang="en">Nature Conservation</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">NC</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1314-6947</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1314-3301</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/natureconservation.62.163636</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">163636</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="biological_taxon">
          <subject>Animalia</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="scientific_subject">
          <subject>Climate change</subject>
          <subject>Ecology &amp; Environmental sciences</subject>
          <subject>Floodplain</subject>
          <subject>Habitat restoration</subject>
          <subject>Habitats</subject>
          <subject> Ecosystems &amp; Natural Spaces</subject>
          <subject>Restoration ecology</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="geographical_area">
          <subject>Europe</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>European riverine and coastal wetlands under pressure: biodiversity and climate change</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="authors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kaden</surname>
            <given-names>Ute Susanne</given-names>
          </name>
          <email xlink:type="simple">ute-susanne.kaden@ufz.de</email>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-959X</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schmid</surname>
            <given-names>Sophia</given-names>
          </name>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2554-0797</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vieweg</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3454-2281</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scholz</surname>
            <given-names>Mathias</given-names>
          </name>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8463-9500</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dufour</surname>
            <given-names>Simon</given-names>
          </name>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8268-9371</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line content-type="verbatim">UFZ - Helmholtz-Centre for Environmental Research, Department of Conservation Biology and Social Ecological Systems, Permoserstraße 15, 04318 Leipzig, Germany</addr-line>
        <institution>UFZ - Helmholtz-Centre for Environmental Research</institution>
        <addr-line content-type="city">Leipzig</addr-line>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line content-type="verbatim">Université Rennes 2, LETG CNRS UMR 6554, Place le Moal, Rennes, France</addr-line>
        <institution>Université Rennes 2</institution>
        <addr-line content-type="city">Rennes</addr-line>
        <country>France</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Ute Susanne Kaden (<email xlink:type="simple">ute-susanne.kaden@ufz.de</email>)</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: Klement Tockner</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>62</volume>
      <fpage>13</fpage>
      <lpage>45</lpage>
      <uri content-type="arpha" xlink:href="http://openbiodiv.net/3C440BFB-08F3-5F8A-831B-2F39F36AEB5E">3C440BFB-08F3-5F8A-831B-2F39F36AEB5E</uri>
      <uri content-type="zenodo_dep_id" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/0">0</uri>
      <uri content-type="zoobank" xlink:href="https://zoobank.org/55947C31-7C29-47AE-808D-8B427C7B183E">55947C31-7C29-47AE-808D-8B427C7B183E</uri>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Ute Susanne Kaden, Sophia Schmid, Michael Vieweg, Mathias Scholz, Simon Dufour</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="zoobank" xlink:type="simple">https://zoobank.org/55947C31-7C29-47AE-808D-8B427C7B183E</self-uri>
      <abstract>
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p>Although European coastal and riverine wetlands occupy a small share of the European land area, these ecosystems host remarkable biodiversity and provide a wide range of ecosystem services fundamental for human well-being, including clean water, recreation, food provision and climate regulation. Synthesising current knowledge across biogeographic regions, this review shows that only 12% of EU riverine and coastal wetland habitat types are in favourable condition, while the majority continue to deteriorate, mirrored by substantial declines in many wetland-dependent species. Climate-related impacts vary strongly across Europe and interact with existing human pressures such as land-use change, hydromorphological alteration, hydropower, coastal engineering and pollution, accelerating habitat and species loss and reducing the resilience of wetlands to climate change impacts. The paper calls for a rethinking of coastal and riverine wetlands as multifunctional landscapes and stresses the need for coordinated, cross-sectoral policy approaches. These wetlands are positioned not only as vulnerable systems but as pivotal Nature-based Solutions for achieving climate resilience and halting biodiversity loss, while remaining essential resources for human life support.</p>
        <sec sec-type="Highlights" id="sec1">
          <title>Highlights</title>
          <boxed-text position="float">
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Remaining European riverine and coastal wetlands are small and fragmented, yet vital for biodiversity and climate resilience.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Only 12% of EU riverine and coastal wetland habitat types remain in favourable conservation status.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Climate impacts vary regionally and interact with multiple pressures, demanding tailored adaptation strategies.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Wetland multifunctionality makes them key Nature-based Solutions.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Riverine and coastal wetlands must move from the policy periphery to the core of climate-biodiversity action, enabled by an integrated, cross-sectoral restoration and conservation effort.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </boxed-text>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <label>Key words:</label>
        <kwd>Biodiversity loss</kwd>
        <kwd>climate change impacts</kwd>
        <kwd>coasts</kwd>
        <kwd>ecosystem services</kwd>
        <kwd>European wetlands</kwd>
        <kwd>floodplains</kwd>
        <kwd>Nature-based Solutions</kwd>
        <kwd>wetland restoration</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <sec sec-type="Citation" id="sec2">
        <title>Citation</title>
        <p>Kaden US, Schmid S, Vieweg M, Scholz M, Dufour S () European riverine and coastal wetlands under pressure: biodiversity and climate change. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation : –. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.163636" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.163636</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="sec3">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Wetlands are among Europe’s most biodiversity-rich and climate-relevant ecosystems, yet they have undergone extensive degradation over recent decades. Within this broad group, riverine and coastal wetlands form dynamic transition zones between land, freshwater and marine systems. They support unique species assemblages, provide key hydrological and biogeochemical functions, and contribute significantly to climate adaptation and climate change mitigation. These ecosystems are increasingly affected by multiple, interacting pressures, ranging from land-use change, river regulation, hydropower development, coastal engineering and pollution to the accelerating impacts of climate change, resulting in widespread losses of habitat quality and biodiversity. This synthesis provides a concise overview of the current status and climate-related challenges affecting European riverine and coastal wetlands and their associated biodiversity. Besides floodplains and coastal wetlands, mires, bogs and shallow peats represent another important wetland category in Europe. Depending on the biogeographic region, peat-forming habitats can also occur as characteristic components of river floodplains and coastal wetland complexes. Historically covering almost 10% of Europe’s land area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B119">Tanneberger et al. 2017</xref>), peatlands have suffered substantial degradation and losses, in many EU countries exceeding 50% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B120">Tanneberger et al. 2021</xref>), due to exploitation for peat mining and later drainage for agriculture and forestry. As a result, drained peatlands have become major sources of greenhouse gas emissions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Giersbergen et al. 2024</xref>). However, peatlands deserve separate attention, as this review focuses primarily on European floodplains and coastal wetlands. Specifically, it addresses the following guiding questions: What is the current extent and condition of Europe’s riverine and coastal wetlands? How do climate-related hydrological changes affect these systems across different European regions? What biodiversity trends are observed in major wetland-dependent taxa? How can riverine and coastal wetlands contribute to climate resilience? Considering the broader web of pressures that compound these challenges, what are the implications for wetland restoration and conservation? This overview serves as an introduction to the following articles in this Special Issue, which explore the value of wetlands and their Ecosystem Services (<abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>), their role as Nature-based Solutions (NbS), along with restoration opportunities and policy responses in more detail.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="European wetlands: small in area, big in impact and heavily damaged" id="sec4">
      <title>European wetlands: small in area, big in impact and heavily damaged</title>
      <p>The European continent hosts a rich variety of habitats. With its 66,000 km coastline and diverse geography, including major mountain ranges and lowland river systems, a wide variety of wetlands are supported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B130">Verhoeven 2014</xref>). Historically rich in peatlands, floodplains and estuarine areas, Europe’s wetlands host more than 90 habitat types under the European Habitats Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">EU/92/43/EEC 1992</xref>), comprising mainly bogs and fens, rivers and floodplains, coastal and marine wetlands, estuaries and deltas, swamps and marshes, lakes and ponds, as well as human-made wetlands. Wetlands, although small in area (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Box 1</xref>), play a disproportionately important role in forest- and agroecosystem-dominated landscapes, particularly in biodiversity conservation. They are hotspots for biodiversity, provide habitats for thousands of species of aquatic and terrestrial plants and animals, and are critical breeding, resting and feeding grounds for many, especially migratory birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Gopal 2009</xref>). To take it globally, wetlands cover only 7% of the Earth’s land surface, yet they hold most of the planet’s accessible freshwater and provide essential habitats for ~40% of all known species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B137">Wetlands International 2020</xref>). Beyond this, the impact of wetland health in Europe is felt globally, as healthy wetlands also serve as carbon sinks, sequestering carbon and playing a crucial role in mitigating climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">Mitsch et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Ludewig et al. 2026</xref>). More locally, they also play a vital role in adapting to the effects of climate change. Acting as natural sponges, they help regulate the water cycle by receiving and storing excess water during floods and slowly releasing it during droughts (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Acreman and Holden 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Ferreira et al. 2023</xref>). Wetlands also provide a range of provisioning services: their ability to filter nutrients (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B142">Zak et al. 2026</xref>) and trap pollutants makes them essential for maintaining water quality, benefiting both ecosystems and human use by supplying freshwater for drinking and irrigation, along with rice, fish and shellfish from fresh and coastal waters, as well as fibre and fuel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">Ramsar 2018</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bertassello et al. (2025)</xref> estimate that existing European wetlands remove 1,092 (± 95) kt of nitrogen per year (i.e. 6.7% of the current surplus) and that, in the absence of existing wetlands, the nitrogen loads would be ~25% higher. Beyond their ecological functions, wetlands hold deep cultural and spiritual significance by supporting traditional knowledge systems and fostering a sense of place and belonging (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B134">Wantzen and Cao 2026</xref>). Moreover, they provide valuable spaces for recreation, contributing to our physical and mental health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B140">Wood et al. 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">Reimold et al. 1980</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        <label>Box 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>European coastal and riverine wetlands – definitions and extent.<bold/></p>
        </caption>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">As the term itself suggests, wetland is an umbrella term for ecosystems whose formation, functioning and characteristics are primarily shaped and influenced by water. There is no single, universally applicable definition of wetlands, which has led to a variety of definitions and classification systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>, EC 2020a). For example, wetlands can be categorised based on the sources of their water supply. <bold>Coastal wetlands</bold>, influenced by ocean tides, appear as tidal wetlands; <bold>floodplains/riverine wetlands</bold> are primarily shaped by river waters; and estuaries result from a mix of both. Additionally, wetlands may form from groundwater sources, such as springs and fens, or from precipitation and snowmelt, which give rise to bogs and ponds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Keddy 2010</xref>).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One of the most widely recognised definitions is provided by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">Ramsar Convention (1971)</xref>, which describes wetlands as “<italic>[…] areas of marsh, fen, peatland or water, whether natural or artificial, permanent or temporary, with water that is static or flowing, fresh, brackish or salt, including areas of marine water the depth of which at low tide does not exceed six metres</italic>.” (Ramsar 1971).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This definitional variability also affects the estimation of the total extent of wetlands globally and in Europe, as figures vary depending on the classification applied. Moreover, differences in the spatial reference for Europe, whether considered geographically or as EU Member States, and in the data sources used influence the resulting percentages. Therefore, estimates vary between 500,000 km<sup>2</sup>, corresponding to 7% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">Nivet and Frazier 2004</xref>), 174,400 km<sup>2</sup>, corresponding to 4.5% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">EC BISE 2023</xref>), and 73,000 km<sup>2</sup>, corresponding to 1.7% (EC Eurostat 2018). However, according to a new European Wetland Map (<abbrev xlink:title="European Wetland Map">EWM</abbrev>) launched on World Wetlands Day 2025 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B122">Tegetmeyer et al. 2025</xref>), the total wetland area, including floodplains, coastal wetlands, other wetlands and peatlands, sums to ~77,079 km<sup>2</sup>, corresponding to 1.5% of the European land surface (details in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B121">Tegetmeyer et al. 2024</xref>). When peatlands are excluded, this figure drops to 0.75%, as illustrated below by a map compiled from the <abbrev xlink:title="European Wetland Map">EWM</abbrev> dataset, which visualises several riverine and coastal wetland types and includes peatland areas shown in a distinct colour scheme.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <inline-graphic xlink:href="nature_conservation-62-013_article-163636__-i001.jpg" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_1547815.jpg"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resolution and accuracy are strongly constrained by the quality and completeness of the underlying datasets. Due to widely varying mapping scales, divergent national definitions and heterogeneous recording methods, compiling a harmonised European dataset remains highly challenging. As a result, the presented map (see above) deviates substantially from the actual wetland distribution in many regions. Nevertheless, the <abbrev xlink:title="European Wetland Map">EWM</abbrev> represents an important step forward, as it is the first integrated, Europe-wide wetland map produced from multiple open-access datasets, even though the individual layers have been publicly available previously. Its remaining inaccuracies underline the urgent need to further harmonise mapping standards and improve data quality across Europe. None of the datasets used for the <abbrev xlink:title="European Wetland Map">EWM</abbrev> provides an ecological status assessment. For floodplains, evaluations show that in Germany 70–90% of active floodplains have been lost, and only about 10% of the remaining areas are in good condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Koenzen et al. 2021</xref>), consistent with Europe-wide findings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Globevnic et al. (2020)</xref>. Most coastal wetland habitats in the EU are in poor ecological condition, or data are insufficient to reliably assess their status. For peatlands, the most recent European assessments are provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B120">Tanneberger et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Giersbergen et al. (2024)</xref>.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Together, the overall value of these functions, known as Ecosystem Services (<abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>), which contribute to human well-being through food security, biodiversity support, water regulation, climate mitigation and recreation, is immense and far outweighs that of terrestrial ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">de Groot et al. 2012</xref>; Ramsar 2021a; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Jähnig et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Day et al. 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">Stammel et al. 2026</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Davidson et al. (2019)</xref> estimate that the global monetary value of wetland <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> is about USD 47.4 trillion per year; that is 43.5% of the value of all natural biomes for a much lower coverage rate (see above). They also estimate that coastal wetlands, representing only 15% of global wetland area, deliver 43.1% of this value.</p>
      <p>Although wetlands still cover a global area larger than Canada, they have been rapidly declining. Estimates of global wetland loss vary widely due to methodological differences and diverging definitions. For decades, high estimates of wetland loss have been reported in the scientific literature, with claims that up to 50% of the world’s wetlands have been lost since 1900 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B143">Zedler and Kercher 2005</xref>). More recent assessments based on regional extrapolations and geospatial overlays suggest net losses ranging between 33% and 57% since 1900 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Davidson et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Hu et al. 2017</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Fluet-Chouinard et al. (2023)</xref> provide a comprehensive estimate, focusing on inland wetlands, coastal intertidal zones and nearshore marine wetlands. Their findings indicate that natural wetland areas have declined by ~3.4 million km<sup>2</sup> since 1700, corresponding to a 21% loss. North America, Europe, Central Asia, India, China, Japan and Southeast Asia have been identified as hotspots of wetland loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Fluet-Chouinard et al. 2023</xref>).</p>
      <p>In Europe, over the past 250 years, wetlands of all types have been extensively drained, altered and reclaimed, primarily for agriculture, urban development, flood control and transportation, resulting in significant degradation or loss of their ecological functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Junk et al. 2012</xref>). Reported estimates vary significantly across regions, ranging between 45% and 80%, with wetlands in northern Europe generally less affected than those in central and southern regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Hu et al. 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B130">Verhoeven 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Fluet-Chouinard et al. 2023</xref>). In northern Europe, drainage was largely linked to peat extraction and timber logging, while losses in central and southern regions resulted mainly from river straightening and agricultural conversion (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Blackbourn 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Hohensinner et al. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Fluet-Chouinard et al. 2023</xref>). Similar to current wetland extent estimates (<bold>see</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Box 1</xref>), discrepancies in reported wetland loss can be attributed to differences in calculation methods, including varying definitions of wetland degradation, which range along a continuum from complete drainage and land conversion to altered hydrological conditions and soil degradation. The precise quantity of wetland loss in Europe over the past centuries remains uncertain.</p>
      <p>In large river floodplains, the flood pulse was historically unpredictable and often occurred during the growing season, threatening crops and livestock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B124">Tockner et al. 2000</xref>). This unpredictability hindered flood-adapted management and led to the construction of dikes for flood protection, such as the straightening of the Rhine River by engineer Tulla in 19<sup>th</sup>-century Germany (but also along the Danube, the Rhône and many other large European rivers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">Petts 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Hohensinner et al. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B125">Tockner et al. 2022</xref>). The fluvial network is also modified by more than 1.2 million instream barriers in 36 European countries, corresponding to a mean density of 0.74 barriers per kilometre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Belletti et al. 2020</xref>), and less than 23% of large European rivers are still free-flowing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Grill et al. 2019</xref>). Due to their reliance on specific environmental conditions, especially hydrology, floodplains are particularly vulnerable, and even minor changes, such as small fluctuations in water levels, can have major consequences, for example, for water-dependent vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Maltby 2009</xref>). Lastly, land-use changes deeply modify the integrity of riverine wetlands. Based on the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Copernicus Land Monitoring Service (2021)</xref>, it is estimated that only 30% of riverine zone areas across Europe are still forested, whereas they could exceed 95%. Obviously, there are differences between countries: the rate can reach an average of 50% in Scandinavia and fall to 10% in England and Ireland. Moreover, between 2012 and 2018, ~9,000 hectares disappeared each year in Europe. Nearly 50% of these areas were reallocated to built-up areas, 25% to cultivation and 25% to grazing. As a result, only small areas of near-natural floodplains remain today, and 70% to 90% of floodplains in Europe are disconnected from characteristic flooding dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">EEA 2020a</xref>), even though the magnitude and mix of pressures vary across regions. For example, in Scandinavian floodplains, agricultural land-use pressure is lower than in much of the rest of Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B135">Weissteiner et al. 2016</xref>), but extensive hydropower development has fundamentally altered river flows, fragmented channels and degraded floodplain and delta ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">Renöfält et al. 2009</xref>). Whereas in western, central and southern Europe, land conversion, regulation and dams are combined.</p>
      <p>For coastal wetlands, population pressure is a significant driver affecting these ecosystems at both global and continental scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Day et al. 2024</xref>). Indeed, 41% of the EU population lives in Europe’s coastal regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">EEA 2020b</xref>). Coastal wetlands were extensively converted into polders for pasture and cropland, exemplified by the Wadden Sea region in northern Europe, where poldering began in the sixteenth century and ceased in 1954, with the remaining Wadden Sea area now partly protected. However, many other European coastal wetlands also face heavy pressures. In the Mediterranean, areas such as the Camargue in France, the Doñana wetlands and Ebro Delta in Spain, and the Po Delta in Italy are threatened by urban growth, intensive agriculture, water management changes, pollution and infrastructure development. The Danube Delta in Romania and Ukraine, one of Europe’s largest wetlands, is also subject to similar pressures.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="European riverine and coastal wetlands in a changing climate" id="sec5">
      <title>European riverine and coastal wetlands in a changing climate</title>
      <p>European riverine and coastal wetlands are affected by multiple long-standing anthropogenic pressures outlined above. These pressures continue today and are further intensified by climate change, which not only influences the functioning of wetlands but also accelerates the release of greenhouse gases from degraded wetlands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">(IPCC 2023a</xref>) and reduces their capacity to buffer climate-related impacts. The most evident and direct effects of climate change on riverine and coastal wetlands can be broadly grouped into those caused by (1) rising average temperatures, (2) changing precipitation patterns, and (3) the increasing frequency and intensity of extreme weather events – each with regionally and ecologically specific consequences.</p>
      <p>Average climate conditions are expected to continue shifting significantly over the coming decades. As predicted by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (<abbrev xlink:title="Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change">IPCC</abbrev>), rising temperatures and global warming will lead to sea-level rise and an increase in extreme weather events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">IPCC 2023a</xref>). This holds true for Europe as well. Recent trends and future projections for Europe have been inventoried and synthesised in several scientific summaries. According to the European Environment Agency’s report, which draws on peer-reviewed models, datasets and literature, trends in temperature, precipitation and climate extremes, including heatwaves, droughts, heavy precipitation and floods, are projected to intensify across Europe in the coming decade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">EEA 2024a</xref>). The growing intensity and frequency of extremes will strongly affect riverine and coastal wetlands, as they are highly dependent on the hydrological cycle. Their sensitivity to changes in water quantity and quality, driven by altered hydrological regimes, makes them highly vulnerable to climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Erwin 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Harris et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">Moomaw et al. 2018</xref>). As hydrological patterns shift, many local water regimes are becoming wetter or drier. For example, in snow-affected catchments (Central Europe and Eastern Europe), high flows are expected to appear earlier in the year, and the duration and volume of inundation are projected to decrease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109">Schneider et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Fink et al. 2026</xref>). This hydrological regime change is likely to lead to a reduction in habitat for several taxa (fish, vertebrates, water birds and floodplain-specific vegetation) and thus to a loss of biodiversity, floodplain productivity and fish production. However, contradictory results have been reported in Spain, France, southern England and the Benelux countries due to uncertainties in climate modelling for specific seasons. A shift in the water balance towards increased evaporation caused by warmer and longer summers not only leads to increased water loss in wetlands but also reduces the amount of water they receive from surrounding catchments, leading to degradation and loss of both riverine and coastal wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Erwin 2008</xref>). Extreme events can impact species and habitats, leading to changes in species richness and composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Ilg et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Harris et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Fink et al. 2026</xref>). In riverine systems, extreme droughts can affect the total growth frequency of plants and may cause shifts from freshwater- toward salt- or drought-tolerant species, while extreme flooding will reduce the total area of wetland vegetation and lower vegetation diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B141">Xiong et al. 2023</xref>). In coastal wetlands, severe storm surges, erosion events and prolonged inundation can lead to vegetation dieback, reduced sediment accretion and loss of habitat complexity. Thus, the physical impacts of climate change drive biological changes, including shifts in ecosystem structure, species distributions and abundance, altered phenology and physiology, and increased presence of invasive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">Moomaw et al. 2018</xref>). These changes can become long-lasting or irreversible if repeated extreme events occur and may lead to completely new biocoenoses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Hobbs et al. 2006</xref>). In recent decades, extreme biological responses to individual extreme weather events have already been observed in many ecosystems around the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Harris et al. 2018</xref>). These changes also impair ecosystem functions and reduce the provision of key <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>. Some of these important <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> may even turn into disservices. For instance, instead of filtering and purifying water, wetlands may start to release stored nutrients, or when the rate of decomposition surpasses that of primary production (photosynthesis), wetlands may shift from acting as carbon sinks to becoming carbon sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">Salimi et al. 2021</xref>). The impacts of future climate scenarios on <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> provided have been estimated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">Okruszko et al. (2011)</xref> based on a sample of one hundred large wetlands in Europe and several <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> (biodiversity, biomass production, nutrient removal, carbon storage and fish production). They anticipate a loss of between 26% and 46% of all identified <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> by 2050. Moreover, the most significant loss of <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> is expected to occur in Central Europe. Thus, as wetlands degrade, their ability to purify water, regulate floods, support biodiversity and provide resources such as fish and other harvestable goods is diminished (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">MEA 2005</xref>). These processes apply to both riverine and coastal wetlands, although the mechanisms differ (e.g. drying and disconnection in riverine systems and erosion and salinity intrusion in coastal systems).</p>
      <p>Besides these direct impacts of climate change on ecosystem functioning, including changes in community composition and habitat change, wetlands are also affected by indirect pressures arising from changing water and land uses. Climate-change-induced decline in water quality, along with changes in the seasonality and extremity of river hydrology and threats to coastal wetlands from sea-level rise, storm surges and saltwater intrusion, require not only species and communities to adapt to these new conditions. Such changes often trigger management responses, such as strengthened technical flood protection, construction of weirs in the river itself or reservoirs to bridge droughts, resulting in additional water and land-use competition and further destruction of habitats or key site characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">EC 2020a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">EEA 2018</xref>). An illustrative example is the surge in planned hydropower projects across the Balkans, an area identified as a major freshwater biodiversity hotspot in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Carrizo et al. 2017</xref>). Although promoted as a contribution to energy decarbonisation, these projects pose substantial risks to riverine ecosystems and wetland connectivity due to cumulative ecological impacts and disruptions of catchment-scale processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Carolli et al. 2023</xref>). The expression of climate change impacts varies between European regions, and as wetlands are diverse in type and spread across different climatic zones, their responses to climate change will vary accordingly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">BMU et al. 2020</xref>).</p>
      <p>In <bold>coastal wetlands</bold> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Ibáñez et al. 2026</xref>), sea-level rise is expected to be the primary driver of change, particularly along the Atlantic coast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>). Approximately 10% of the world’s population lives in areas less than 10 metres above sea level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">McGranahan et al. 2007</xref>), many of which are economically important regions such as river deltas. Given this, the most immediate and severe impacts of inundation through sea-level rise, accompanied by habitat loss and socioeconomic disruption, are expected to occur in these low-lying coastal areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">FitzGerald et al. 2008</xref>). Under high-emission scenarios, projections suggest that between 20% and 90% of today’s coastal wetland areas could be lost by 2100, depending on the magnitude of sea-level rise and the region’s capacity for inland migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">Schuerch et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112">Spencer et al. 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">IPCC 2023b</xref>). As the ability of coastal wetlands to shift landwards in response to rising sea levels is often prevented by human-made structures (a phenomenon known as “coastal squeeze”; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Doody 2013</xref>), and sediment supply is disrupted, coastal vulnerability is further exacerbated. For example, in Denmark, extensive dikes, seawalls and other infrastructure prevent the natural inland migration of wetlands. A recent nationwide analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Canal-Vergés et al. 2024</xref>) predicts that by 2120, almost half (45%) of all Danish coastal wetlands will be permanently inundated under a medium sea-level rise scenario. In the Mediterranean countries, including France, a study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B131">Verniest et al. (2024)</xref> found that by 2100, one-third to more than half of the &gt; 900 analysed coastal wetlands could be submerged.</p>
      <p><bold>Southern Europe</bold> is, in addition to the challenges posed by sea-level rise, generally expected to face the greatest challenges from water shortages and intensifying competition for water resources among agriculture, industry, settlements and nature conservation efforts, including wetland protection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>). Even under moderate emission scenarios, droughts are projected to become increasingly frequent and severe, especially in the southern and western parts of Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">EC 2020a</xref>). Under high-emission scenarios, summer drought frequency in the Mediterranean could rise by up to 40% by 2100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">Spinoni et al. 2017</xref>), and under a 3 °C warming, absolute drought damages in the Mediterranean subregion are expected to quintuple, far exceeding those in northern Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">EC 2020a</xref>). Although overall precipitation in the Mediterranean region is projected to decrease, heavy rainfall events are expected to become more frequent and intense, particularly in northern areas, raising the risk of flash floods in vulnerable coastal zones such as Turkey, Greece, Italy, France and Spain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">MedECC 2020</xref>).</p>
      <p>In contrast, <bold>northern (boreal) Europe</bold> is projected to experience a small but sustained decrease in droughts, a trend expected to continue under future warming scenarios (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">EEA 2021</xref>). While most of southern Europe is expected to see a decrease in annual precipitation, northern Europe is projected to experience the opposite trend. However, even with increased precipitation, warmer temperatures accelerate microbial decomposition and seasonally dry surface layers. These effects mainly destabilise the wetland types dominant in this region, floodplains with mainly organic soils, bogs and fens, which have historically been important for storing vast amounts of carbon, relying on waterlogged, low-oxygen conditions. Warmer conditions also increase the risk of peat fires and permafrost thaw, further altering their hydrology and species composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B126">Turetsky et al. 2020</xref>). This shift threatens to turn these once-stable, mainly peat-rich wetlands from long-term carbon sinks into net sources of greenhouse gases, accelerating the climate change feedback loop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Harenda et al. 2017</xref>). However, changes in snowmelt timing, runoff seasonality and increased winter rainfall also affect riverine and coastal wetlands, altering hydrological regimes and water levels. Thus, in addition to the large-scale destruction caused by drainage, hydropower, forestry and land-use changes, warming and its accompanying effects will have profound impacts on biodiversity, water quality and the global carbon budget (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">Salimi et al. 2021</xref>).</p>
      <p><bold>Central and Western Europe</bold> are likely to be among the regions most affected by extreme weather events and their consequences, such as heavy rainfall followed by flooding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>). Precipitation-driven river flood hazards in Western and Central Europe have already grown by ~11% per decade from 1960–2010 and are projected to rise further, by roughly 10% at 2 °C global warming and ~18% at 4.4 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bednar-Friedl et al. 2022</xref>). These changing precipitation regimes also imply more severe summer droughts. Hotter summers, with higher evapotranspiration, are drying soils and reducing snow and glacier melt inputs, making rivers more dependent on rainfall. Alpine snowmelt-driven summer floods are expected to decline at ~2 °C warming, whereas winter and spring floods are expected to increase due to heavier rainfall and earlier snowmelt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bednar-Friedl et al. 2022</xref>). Given the high population density in these regions, rising flood risks may fuel political pressure for hard flood-defence measures, potentially to the detriment of wetland hydrology and ecological functions if NbS are not prioritised.</p>
      <p>It is worth noting that a major challenge, both scientific and applied, lies in the ability to account for the multiple pressures that interact. In fact, climate change, beyond its individual effects, is adding additional pressure to environments that are already subject to many pressures in terms of both water quality and quantity. This multi-pressure context is (1) still poorly taken into account (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">Martínez-Megías and Rico 2022</xref>) and (2) a challenge because the pressures are not just added but combine in very complex ways (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B115">Stella and Bendix 2019</xref>). Neglecting the impact of multiple pressures can lead to maladaptation, such as the construction of hard flood defences that disrupt lateral river floodplain connectivity. Even amid uncertainties, Nature-based Solutions (see 3.2.) must become central to climate resilience planning.</p>
      <p>This complexity also applies to climate models predicting wetland responses. Climate change will significantly alter European freshwater wetland distributions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">Schleupner 2011</xref>), but despite advances in climate modelling, considerable uncertainty remains, particularly regarding local hydrological impacts on floodplains and coastal wetlands. Downscaling global or regional climate models to site-specific conditions is challenging due to complex interactions between climate variables, hydrology and land use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Marchi et al. 2020</xref>). Most large-scale models and drought indices (e.g. the Wetlands Drought Index) are primarily precipitation-driven and are not calibrated for the unique hydrological regimes of wetlands in general, often failing to account for river discharge, groundwater dynamics, capillary rise and local land-use interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Copernicus Global Drought Observatory 2024</xref>). While these tools offer standardised, globally applicable monitoring, they risk misrepresenting conditions, particularly where wetlands are buffered by deep aquifers or are highly sensitive to even minor hydrological changes. Addressing these gaps will require the development of wetland-specific monitoring and modelling frameworks that integrate local hydrological data, land use and climate projections, ensuring more accurate predictions and effective adaptation strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Acreman et al. 2007</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="European riverine and coastal wetlands biodiversity in decline" id="sec6">
      <title>European riverine and coastal wetlands biodiversity in decline</title>
      <p>The full diversity of all (healthy) wetland types represents a significant reservoir of biodiversity, playing a crucial role in sustaining species richness and ecological resilience. Biodiversity is not only of intrinsic ecological value but also fundamental to human well-being (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">MEA 2005</xref>). Functional species assemblages maintain water purification, nutrient retention, carbon sequestration, coastal protection and flood mitigation, and many wetlands support fisheries, grazing systems and cultural landscapes. Many endemic species occur exclusively in specific wetland areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">Ramsar 2018</xref>). It is estimated that ~40% of the world’s plant and animal species are dependent on wetlands, including 30% of all known fish species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">Ramsar 2021b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B127">UNFCC 2018</xref>). This global significance is equally evident in Europe. For example, a local study conducted at thirty sites covering just 7.2 km<sup>2</sup> (i.e. 0.0013% of France’s land area) in the alluvial plain of the Adour in south-western France identified almost 1,500 plant species, representing around 15% of the French flora (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117">Tabacchi and Tabacchi 2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Riverine and coastal wetlands represent a significant ecological niche, providing habitat for numerous threatened amphibians and reptiles, hosting migratory and resident water birds, and sustaining thousands of plant species. This is linked to (1) their unique conditions compared to surrounding terrestrial areas, such as flatter topography and distinctive hydrological regimes, allowing specialised species to thrive; (2) their high local variability in space and time, creating numerous ecological niches; and (3) the diverse array of wetland types, each supporting distinct assemblages of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B105">Sabo et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Junk et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Keddy 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">Ramey and Richardson 2017</xref>).</p>
      <p>As they are tightly coupled to hydrological and coastal dynamics, the human- and climate-related changes outlined in the previous sections are already translating into measurable biodiversity impacts across Europe’s riverine and coastal wetlands. Water birds, for example, are facing multiple pressures associated with climate change, such as sea-level rise, temperature fluctuations and altered precipitation patterns, all of which are expected to drive significant habitat loss. Across Europe, ~45% of waterbird populations along the Africa–Eurasia flyway show declining trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B139">Wetlands International 2025</xref>), highlighting the sensitivity of wetland-dependent species to climate-driven hydrological change. In the Ebro Delta, species distribution models project that up to 70% of water bird habitat could disappear by 2100 due to rising sea levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">De la Cruz and Numa 2024</xref>). Similar patterns are observed in other wetland-associated taxa. Migratory European freshwater fish populations have declined by 75% in recent decades due to habitat loss and fragmentation. This has been driven largely by the conversion of wetlands for agricultural use, hydropower development and the lack of free-flowing rivers, with more than 1.2 million anthropogenic barriers in European rivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Belletti et al. 2020</xref>; WWF 2024; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116">Stoffers et al. 2026</xref>). Amphibian data reinforce these trends across European wetlands. Amphibians, which are highly dependent on shallow aquatic habitats, show some of the most profound declines. Nearly one third of species are currently considered threatened in Europe. An additional 8% are categorised as Near Threatened. Priority conservation challenges identified in recent assessments emphasise anthropogenic pressures that have intensified over the past decade. Central among these are the spread of invasive species, the emergence of pathogens such as chytrid fungi, and increasing levels of chemical and nutrient pollution, all of which affect small water bodies and other amphibian breeding sites. Habitat destruction and degradation remain pervasive, particularly the loss of structurally complex aquatic habitats that support both adult and larval stages. These patterns highlight the disproportionate vulnerability of amphibians to hydrological disturbance and habitat fragmentation within wetland systems. Invertebrate data reveal similar patterns. Recent assessments of European dragonflies and damselflies (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order" reg="Odonata">Odonata</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) highlight that ~21% of the 146 species assessed are threatened, with an additional 12% classified as Near Threatened (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">De Knijf et al. 2024</xref>). These taxa are particularly vulnerable to a range of anthropogenic pressures. Populations are threatened or destroyed by increased water abstraction, especially for agricultural use; water pollution combined with elevated nutrient loads; channelisation; gravel extraction; and the widespread use of pesticides and herbicides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">De Knijf et al. 2024</xref>).</p>
      <p>These indicators, demonstrating a decline across multiple taxa in European riverine and coastal wetland biodiversity, are also mirrored globally. Since 1970, populations of inland wetland species have decreased by 81%, while coastal and marine wetland species have seen a 36% decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">Ramsar 2018</xref>). The decline of species is closely mirrored by the degradation and loss of the habitats on which they depend. An overview of habitat trends provides essential context for interpreting the species-level declines described above and underscores the scale of conservation action required (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Box 2</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        <label>Box 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of the status of European riverine and coastal wetland habitat types.</p>
        </caption>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This overview draws on EU Member States’ conservation status assessments (2013–2018). Annex I of the European Habitats Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">EU/92/43/EEC 1992</xref>) lists 233 habitat types of European importance. The European Environment Agency (EEA) classifies 82 of these Annex I habitat types as wetland-related, including coastal, freshwater, peatland and riparian habitats, defined largely by their plant species composition. For the analysis of riverine and coastal wetland habitat types, six habitat categories were identified: (i) coastal and halophytic habitats, (ii) dunes, (iii) grasslands, (iv) freshwater habitats, (v) bogs and mires, and (vi) forests, including only those habitat types that occur naturally within floodplain or coastal wetland complexes (see Appendix <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1">1</xref> for the detailed list).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <inline-graphic xlink:href="nature_conservation-62-013_article-163636__-i002.jpg" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_1547816.jpg"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A detailed examination of the Annex I habitat types can facilitate an understanding of the current status of riverine and coastal wetlands in Europe. The conservation status assessments of European coastal and riverine wetland habitats show that the vast majority are in bad or inadequate ecological condition. Only 12% of the assessed habitat types are classified as favourable, whereas 39% are inadequate and 45% are in a bad conservation status. This finding suggests not only widespread degradation across Europe’s biogeographical regions but also that many habitats are failing to meet minimum ecological requirements for maintaining biodiversity and ecosystem functioning.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">These results align with broader assessments of ecosystem condition across Europe, where wetlands remain among the most threatened ecosystems (EEA 2020c). Notably, riverine and coastal wetlands perform worse in comparison with the average across all Annex I habitat types (36% bad, 45% inadequate, 15% favourable). The poor conservation status of these wetland habitats reflects how severely these ecosystems are threatened, fragmented and reshaped by human activities, with climate change-related pressures such as changes in precipitation and discharge, rising temperatures and rising sea levels further weakening key ecological processes (EC 2020c). The loss of habitats, their species and ecological functions directly reduces the capacity of these wetlands to support human societies, as these functions sustain the wide range of ecosystem services essential to human well-being, including water purification, flood regulation, shoreline protection, carbon storage, food provision, and recreational and cultural values.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>In conclusion, the dominance of inadequate and bad conservation statuses across European coasts and floodplain habitats (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Box 2</xref>) points not only to a severe and ongoing decline in biodiversity but also to a weakening of the very functions that enable wetlands to buffer climate impacts. Climate change accelerates biodiversity decline through altered hydrology, extreme events and rising temperatures, while biodiversity loss, in turn, reduces wetlands’ capacity to regulate floods, store carbon, and dissipate wave energy. For example, coastal wetlands can reduce wave energy by up to 60% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">Möller et al. 2014</xref>), meaning that degradation of marsh or saltgrass habitats directly diminishes natural coastal protection. Similarly, structurally degraded floodplains store less floodwater and stabilise banks less effectively, reducing resilience to hydrological extremes. These dynamics illustrate that biodiversity not only responds to climate change but also actively shapes the extent to which wetlands can mitigate its impacts.</p>
      <p>This reciprocal relationship creates a reinforcing cycle of vulnerability. Breaking this cycle requires restoring wetland habitats, improving ecological connectivity and reducing anthropogenic pressures, particularly in regions where habitats are in poor condition. Reconnecting rivers and their floodplains and restoring coastal wetlands are essential steps to restore ecological integrity and secure climate resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">EEA 2024b</xref>). Ultimately, separating climate and biodiversity policy frameworks risks undermining progress on both agendas. Addressing these crises in an integrated manner is therefore essential, and the restoration of wetlands provides a prime example of an intervention that simultaneously mitigates climate impacts and halts biodiversity loss.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Mitigation and adaptation: wetland-based opportunities for climate resilience" id="sec7">
      <title>Mitigation and adaptation: wetland-based opportunities for climate resilience</title>
      <p>Climate regulation, as well as the role of wetlands in buffering the effects of climate change, is identified among the key Ecosystem Services (<abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>) provided by all kinds of wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">Moomaw et al. 2018</xref>). Consequently, restored wetlands can be essential components of climate change adaptation and mitigation strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Erwin 2008</xref>). While adaptation focuses on climate change impacts by enabling communities and ecosystems to adjust to present or anticipated effects, thereby enhancing resilience, mitigation targets the root causes of climate change by reducing greenhouse gas emissions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Kaden et al. 2023</xref>).</p>
      <p>Coastal and riverine wetlands provide essential services that support <bold>climate adaptation</bold> to various hydroclimatic challenges. Their capacity to buffer environmental variability is determined by their hydrological connectivity, landscape position and biogeochemical processes, making them critical components of nature-based adaptation strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Capon et al. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Junk et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Fuller et al. 2022</xref>). In the context of increasing frequency and intensity of freshwater floods, floodplains attenuate peak flows by retaining floodwaters, thereby reducing the magnitude of downstream flooding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Acreman and Holden 2013</xref>). Thus, wetland restoration actions (e.g. blocking drainage, avoiding the removal of aquatic vegetation) can mitigate part of the current effects of climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Berezowski et al. 2018</xref>). Acting as natural sponges, riverine wetlands modulate hydrological extremes through water retention and gradual release of stored water during dry periods, contributing to the regulation of flow regimes and recharge of groundwater aquifers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Granata and Di Nunno 2025</xref>), thereby also improving water quality. For example, the Dutch “Room for the River” programme, involving various interventions (levee setbacks, side-channel deepening and floodplain area expansion), effectively reduced flood risk during extreme events, safeguarding urban infrastructure while enhancing ecological connectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Klijn et al. 2018</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B138">Wetlands International (2022)</xref> synthesises the broader climate-adaptation contributions of wetlands, which extend beyond flood control. For riverine wetlands, these include drought resilience through baseflow maintenance and aquifer recharge, buffering seasonal runoff variability in snow- and glacier-influenced catchments by retaining high-flow pulses, and releasing water during dry periods. Coastal wetlands contribute differently but complementarily. In addition to protection against storm surges, they support sea-level rise adaptation through land accretion and the protection of fishery and freshwater resources. Coastal wetlands also play a role in preventing saltwater intrusion and coastal storm defence by dissipating wave energy and supporting community recovery after extreme events. Approaches such as coastal realignment strategically restore wetland buffers to strengthen these protective functions (see de la<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28"> Vega Leinert et al. 2026</xref>).</p>
      <p>Next to riverine and coastal wetlands being key Nature-based Solutions for climate adaptation, they are also integral to <bold>climate change mitigation</bold> by acting as long-term carbon sinks that store large amounts of atmospheric carbon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">Mitsch et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B136">Were et al. 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Ludewig et al. 2026</xref>). For example, globally, tidal wetlands accumulate about 53.65 Tg C yr<sup>−1</sup> (95% CI: 48.52–59.01) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B133">Wang et al. 2020</xref>). Carbon sequestration takes place when plants fix atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> via photosynthesis and then transfer that carbon into biomass and, ultimately, into soils, where it accumulates over time as carbon stocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B136">Were et al. 2019</xref>). Carbon stocks, sequestration rates and the nature of the responsible processes vary by ecosystem type, leading to a functional classification of carbon pools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abdul Malak et al. 2021</xref>). In this context, referring to the role of carbon in climate change mitigation via sequestration, many studies have focused on blue carbon, which refers to carbon stored in coastal and marine ecosystems such as salt marshes and seagrasses, or green carbon, carbon sequestered by terrestrial ecosystems. However, teal carbon, describing carbon accumulated in freshwater wetlands, has only recently entered the carbon colour nomenclature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B144">Zinke 2020</xref>). Assuming total European wetlands cover around 370,000 km<sup>2</sup> (~7% of EU-27 + UK), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abdul Malak et al. (2021)</xref> estimate vast carbon stocks, between 12 and 31 Gt CO<sub>2</sub>-eq, equivalent to 3–8 years of regional greenhouse gas emissions, and sequestration rates between 24 and 144 Mt CO2-eq per year, offsetting 1–4% of current annual emissions. The European wetland habitats most relevant for this carbon storage include healthy mires, bogs and fens, intact salt marshes, and well-functioning riparian, fluvial and swamp forests, with peatlands holding by far the largest long-term carbon stocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abdul Malak et al. 2021</xref>). However, riverine and coastal wetlands, including riparian forests, floodplains and salt marshes, provide high annual sequestration rates and play a key role in short- to mid-term carbon cycling, with floodplain (riparian) forests, for example, reaching sequestration rates of up to 103–217 g C m<sup>−2</sup> yr<sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abdul Malak et al. 2021</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Ludewig et al. 2026</xref> for further empirical data). Crucially, human degradation, such as drainage and land conversion, can reverse wetland function, turning them from carbon sinks into CO<sub>2</sub> sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">Taillardat et al. 2020</xref>). In general, wetlands play a role in the greenhouse gas (GHG) balance beyond CO<sub>2</sub>: they are sources of non-CO<sub>2</sub> greenhouse gases such as methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) and nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O) as a result of anaerobic decomposition of organic matter, and this production is higher than in upland ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">Neubauer and Megonigal 2015</xref>). Although emitted in much smaller quantities than CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O are far more potent greenhouse gases, with global warming potentials about 28–34 times (CH<sub>4</sub>) and 26–298 times (N<sub>2</sub>O) higher than CO<sub>2</sub> over a 100-year timescale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">IPCC 2023c</xref>). Overall, net GHG fluxes in both riverine and coastal wetlands are complex and shaped by abiotic and biotic factors: hydrology, soil oxygen availability and nutrient levels interact with biotic components (microbial communities, vegetation and organic matter dynamics), thereby determining net fluxes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">Mitsch et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B142">Zak et al. 2026</xref>). In freshwater wetlands, high water tables promote anoxic conditions, therefore boosting CH<sub>4</sub> emissions, while fluctuating or lowered water tables enhance N<sub>2</sub>O production by creating oxic-anoxic transitions. In coastal wetlands, CH<sub>4</sub> emissions are typically low because sulphate-rich tidal waters inhibit methanogenesis, and N<sub>2</sub>O emissions are mainly controlled by tidal flushing and external nitrogen inputs.</p>
      <p>It is important to emphasise that, while wetland restoration is highlighted for its climate change mitigation potential, the conservation and restoration of riverine and coastal wetlands deliver a much wider suite of additional co-benefits (biodiversity, water quality and related services) that are substantial at the landscape scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Jay and Plieninger 2025</xref>). For example, restoring 27% of wetlands historically drained for agriculture could reduce current nitrogen loads to the sea by 36%, while a less disruptive scenario, targeting wetlands on farmlands projected to be abandoned, would still achieve a 22% reduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bertassello et al. 2025</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="From knowledge to action – implications for restoration and conservation" id="sec8">
      <title>From knowledge to action – implications for restoration and conservation</title>
      <p>European riverine and coastal wetlands are situated at the intersection of several environmental crises: climate change, biodiversity loss, land-use changes, exploitation of freshwater resources and pollution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Junk et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">Rodríguez-González et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B132">von Unger et al. 2022</xref>). They have been massively degraded over the past centuries through drainage, land-use change, pollution and fragmentation. Climate change is exacerbating these dynamics, for example, by intensifying periods of drought or accelerating the release of greenhouse gases from degraded wetlands. They are disproportionately vulnerable, as they are highly sensitive to changes in water availability, nutrient loading, chemical contamination and temperature shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">Moomaw et al. 2018</xref>). These pressures are not only interconnected but also mutually reinforcing and pose a major challenge to ecological and social resilience. However, they can also be tackled together, as healthy floodplains and coastal wetlands have the potential to provide an integrated solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B128">Urbanič et al. 2022</xref>). Research findings show that functional riverine and coastal wetlands offer great potential for Nature-based Solutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Kaden et al. 2023</xref>), with a favourable cost-effectiveness ratio precisely due to this advanced state of deterioration. Indeed, wetland restoration or recreation has measurable positive effects on biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (<abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>) with relatively small investments in terms of funding or land area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B123">Thiere et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">Meli et al. 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Berezowski et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Feld et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111">Serra-Llobet et al. 2022</xref>). Thus, they enable cost-effective measures to restore ecosystem functions and enhance resilience to extreme weather events (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Birk et al. 2026</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">Stammel et al. 2026</xref>).</p>
      <p>In recent years, the political landscape has increasingly addressed challenges of ecosystem degradation, with wetlands receiving growing attention due to their ecological significance and vulnerability. However, much of this focus has centred on peatlands because of their carbon relevance, while riverine and coastal wetlands, such as floodplains, deltas and coastal marshes, have received comparatively less attention, despite their high multifunctionality and crucial role in climate resilience. At the global level, the Ramsar Convention on Wetlands, adopted in 1971 and in force since 1975, is dedicated specifically to the conservation and sustainable management of wetlands. The Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework, adopted in 2022 under the Convention on Biological Diversity, sets out global objectives aimed at halting biodiversity loss and restoring degraded ecosystems.</p>
      <p>At the European level, the EU launched its new Biodiversity Strategy for 2030 as part of the European Green Deal, providing a renewed policy framework for halting biodiversity loss and promoting ecosystem restoration. The European Habitats and Birds Directives, with the Natura 2000 network, play a central role in this. Currently, 26% of the EU’s land is covered by protected areas, with the target set to increase this to at least 30% by 2030. Furthermore, the EU strategy calls for strictly protecting one-third of existing protected areas and effectively managing all protected areas by setting clear conservation objectives, implementing targeted measures and monitoring their success. Key restoration measures include integrating biodiversity-rich landscape features on agricultural land, which makes up the majority of European wetlands; halting the decline of pollinators; reducing the use and risk of pesticides by 50% by 2030; and restoring at least 25,000 km of rivers to a free-flowing state – just to name a few (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116">Stoffers et al. 2026</xref>).</p>
      <p>Further strengthening the EU’s legal commitment to restoration, the Nature Restoration Regulation entered into force in 2024 with binding restoration targets for degraded ecosystems, including wetlands. By 2030, Member States are required to implement restoration measures on at least 20% of the EU’s land and sea areas, with the ambition to extend these efforts to all ecosystems in need of restoration by 2050 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Hering et al. 2023</xref>). The regulation focuses particularly on habitats and species covered by existing EU directives and introduces a binding, outcome-oriented implementation mechanism aimed at achieving measurable improvements across diverse ecosystem types – from wetlands and forests to rivers and urban green spaces. The central and complex challenge lies in the implementation of these goals and requires coherent action at several levels. Despite existing scientific knowledge, political strategies and legal frameworks, practical implementation is often fragmented, slow or insufficiently coordinated (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B128">Urbanič et al. 2022</xref>).</p>
      <p>Effective implementation requires the translation of European goals into national and local strategies with clear and effective measures. Successful implementation also involves coordinating EU policies such as the EU Biodiversity Strategy, the Nature Directives, the Water Framework Directive, the Flood Directive, the Climate Strategy and the Marine Strategy Framework Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">Pröbstl et al. 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Klusmann et al. 2026</xref>). However, the lack of coordination is not limited to environmental policies. Cross-sectoral cooperation is needed, for example, in collaboration with agriculture and the Common Agricultural Policy (<abbrev xlink:title="Common Agricultural Policy">CAP</abbrev>) (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">Rouillard et al. 2026</xref>). Indeed, the <abbrev xlink:title="Common Agricultural Policy">CAP</abbrev> incorporates some environmental ambitions related to wetlands (e.g. buffer zones), but the mechanisms by which farmers and landowners receive rewards or compensation for sustainable practices remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Englund et al. 2021</xref>). Moreover, a good articulation between conservation and restoration versus human activities implies opening the box of what we call human activities. For example, in many floodplains and coastal ecosystems, there are substantial differences between intensive and extensive uses, with major implications for conservation and restoration strategies.</p>
      <p>Multifunctionality can support action planning by considering the multiple dimensions and services provided by riverine and coastal wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">Schindler et al. 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Jähnig et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">Stammel et al. 2026</xref>). However, this is sometimes inconceivable at the level of individual wetlands due to trade-offs between different objectives but can be achieved at the landscape scale, where various objectives are optimised across different wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Jay and Plieninger 2025</xref>). This, however, complicates management, as it involves more actors and requires strong coordination across territories and scales.</p>
      <p>Small wetlands are often in worse condition than larger, more emblematic wetlands (e.g. Ramsar sites). They are mostly found on private land and scattered throughout the landscape, forming a dense network that is critical for achieving this landscape-scale multifunctionality. However, their private ownership adds challenges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Dufour et al. 2020</xref>). Effective conservation, management or restoration therefore requires strengthening place-based, bottom-up approaches (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Kmetova-Biro et al. 2026</xref>). Such approaches are also needed, as the extent to which floodplains and coastal wetlands provide different functions varies considerably depending on local hydrology, landscape configuration and ecosystem type (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Bullock and Acreman 2003</xref>). This means providing local managers with adequate resources, such as funding, time, technical support, clear regulations and training, to carry out ambitious plans and projects.</p>
      <p>Therefore, understanding and dealing with people’s perceptions and opinions about wetlands is also critical, as they may differ from experts’ assessments and thus lead to misunderstandings between stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Cottet et al. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Arsénio et al. 2019</xref>). To tackle this, it is essential to deepen research into the social dimensions of wetlands (economic, cultural and related aspects) and to train managers to move beyond solely biophysical approaches towards more holistic, socio-ecological management that incorporates co-creation, place-based and community-driven methods. This also implies (1) promoting a deep understanding of the economic determinants of the multiple pressures exerted on wetlands and (2) providing the cultural, political and financial means to work towards the removal, or reduction, of these pressures. Without this, restoration work risks becoming an endless process.</p>
      <p>From a socio-economic perspective, restoration is not a cost factor but an investment in the future (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Macháč et al. 2026</xref>). Greater socio-economic recognition of wetlands also depends on developing widely accepted methods to economically value their Ecosystem Services (<abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev>) such as carbon sequestration, climate regulation and flood mitigation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>). According to estimates, every euro invested in ecosystem restoration generates multiple benefits, for example, through reduced risks, lower health costs and improved <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> (e.g. between 8 and 38 euros per euro invested; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">EC 2021</xref>).</p>
      <p>Monitoring and success control should not be overlooked. Robust, target-oriented monitoring systems are a prerequisite for efficient planning and implementation. Such systems form the scientific basis for impact control and evaluation, enabling the use of experience gained to further develop implementation strategies or to intervene and adapt to complex environmental conditions (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Cvijanović et al. 2026</xref>).</p>
      <p>Admittedly, climate change poses an additional threat to European riverine and coastal wetlands, on top of historical and ongoing human impacts. However, it also offers the opportunity to develop adaptive wetland management and restore lost and degraded systems if we change our attitude towards them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Čížková et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">Rodríguez-González et al. 2022</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Conclusion" id="sec9">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The position of riverine and coastal wetlands at the interface of climate and biodiversity challenges demonstrates how deeply intertwined these crises are and underscores the need for integrated responses. However, we conclude by emphasising the need to clearly distinguish biodiversity loss from climate change, warning against framing them as competing issues. It is counterproductive to pit climate protection against the biodiversity crisis. Biodiversity must step out of the shadow of the climate debate, as functional ecosystems, especially wetlands, are far more than carbon sinks; they are living, complex systems possessing intrinsic and irreplaceable values beyond their utility to humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Glaubrecht 2025</xref>).</p>
      <p>The United Nations’ biodiversity goals highlight the urgency of not only mitigating climate change but also reversing decades of biodiversity neglect. Decades of insufficient prioritisation and fragmented conservation efforts have contributed to a significant decline in global biodiversity, with many species already extinct or at risk of extinction within the coming decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">IPBES 2019</xref>). Protecting large and connected wetland areas helps preserve whole ecosystems, not just isolated species. Thus, the solution lies in giving more space back to nature through effective protection, habitat restoration and sustainable land management – approaches that must be integrated with climate strategies rather than treated as trade-offs. While climate change mitigation, such as reducing CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, is crucial, it alone cannot halt the biodiversity crisis. However, healthy, functioning ecosystems such as wetlands have the unique capacity to maintain critical Ecosystem Services while simultaneously preserving irreplaceable forms of life. Protecting connected natural areas is essential for maintaining carbon sequestration, water purification, pollination, nutrient cycling, soil stability and agricultural productivity, which benefit both nature and people.</p>
      <p>Complementary to the global targets emphasising the expansion of protected areas, the European Union is simultaneously taking action through its Nature Restoration Regulation (NRR), which aims to restore at least 20% of degraded ecosystems by 2030 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Hering et al. 2023</xref>). By not focusing solely on protected areas but also on enhancing the ecological integrity of managed and multifunctional landscapes, including agricultural and urban zones, the NRR offers a restoration vision emphasising ecological functionality and connectivity across the entire landscape. However, a point often insufficiently implemented or prioritised is the scientific evaluation of restoration success. Robust, target-oriented monitoring systems are essential to track progress, assess effectiveness and provide the evidence base for adaptive management.</p>
      <p>Riverine and coastal wetlands emerge as particularly strategic ecosystems and must be considered critical in all conservation and restoration strategies, as they are among the most efficient ecosystem types in terms of <abbrev xlink:title="Ecosystem Services">ES</abbrev> and biodiversity. Furthermore, they are cost-effective strategies, as they provide services and host biodiversity even in small areas, which is an advantage in densely populated landscapes such as those in the EU. This does not imply that other ecosystems should be neglected.</p>
      <p>Realising this potential requires rethinking riverine and coastal wetlands as complex socio-ecological systems. This requires approaches that manage these ecosystems both as crucial human life resources and as highly diverse ecosystems. Achieving this demand combining strict protection of remaining intact wetlands, which remains challenging, especially in the absence of political will, with adaptive management practices that genuinely integrate sustainable human uses in and around wetlands, and with restoration actions co-constructed with all relevant stakeholders. Such an approach will be essential to facilitate the scaling up of efforts and the definition of shared objectives across governance levels, ensuring benefits for both humans and nature alike. Therefore, political, technical and cultural dimensions must be deeply integrated with ecological ambitions.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="Additional information" id="sec10">
      <title>Additional information</title>
      <sec sec-type="Conflict of interest" id="sec11">
        <title>Conflict of interest</title>
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Ethical statement" id="sec12">
        <title>Ethical statement</title>
        <p>No ethical statement was reported.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Use of AI" id="sec13">
        <title>Use of AI</title>
        <p>No use of AI was reported.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Funding" id="sec14">
        <title>Funding</title>
        <p>Supported by the Federal Agency for Nature Conservation (BfN) with funds from the Federal Ministry for the Environment, Nature Conservation, Nuclear Safety and Consumer Protection (BMUKN) (Project No. 3521830200), the Horizon 2020 Framework Programme of the European Union, notably COST Action CONVERGES, the LIFE Programme (LIFE IP ARTISAN), and the Horizon Europe projects SpongeBoost (Grant Agreement No. 101112906), Restore4Life (Grant Agreement No. 101112736), RESPIN (Grant Agreement No. 101135490) and MERLIN (Grant Agreement No. 101036337).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Author contributions" id="sec15">
        <title>Author contributions</title>
        <p>U.S.K. and S.S. contributed to the conceptualisation and methodology of the study. Formal analysis was carried out by U.S.K., S.S., M.S. and M.V. Resources were provided by U.S.K., S.S., M.V., M.S. and S.D. The original draft of the manuscript was written by U.S.K. and S.S. All authors (U.S.K., S.S., M.V., M.S. and S.D.) contributed to the review and editing of the manuscript. Visualisation was handled by S.S. and M.V. Supervision was provided by M.S. and S.D., while project administration was managed by U.S.K., S.S. and M.S.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Author ORCIDs" id="sec16">
        <title>Author ORCIDs</title>
        <p>Ute Susanne Kaden <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-959X" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-959X</ext-link></p>
        <p>Sophia Schmid <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2554-0797" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2554-0797</ext-link></p>
        <p>Michael Vieweg <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3454-2281" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3454-2281</ext-link></p>
        <p>Mathias Scholz <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8463-9500" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8463-9500</ext-link></p>
        <p>Simon Dufour <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8268-9371" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8268-9371</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Data availability" id="sec17">
        <title>Data availability</title>
        <p>All of the data that support the findings of this study are available in the main text.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation>Abdul Malak D, Marin AI, Trombetti M, San Roman S (2021) Carbon pools and sequestration potential of wetlands in the European Union. European Topic Centre on Urban, Land and Soil Systems, Viena and Malaga, 56 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eionet.europa.eu/etcs/etc-uls/products/etc-uls-reports/etc-uls-2021-3-carbon-pools-and-sequestration-potential-of-wetlands-in-the-european-union" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eionet.europa.eu/etcs/etc-uls/products/etc-uls-reports/etc-uls-2021-3-carbon-pools-and-sequestration-potential-of-wetlands-in-the-european-union</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation>Acreman M, Holden J (2013) How Wetlands Affect Floods. Wetlands 33: 773–786. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s13157-013-0473-2" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13157-013-0473-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation>Acreman MC, Fisher J, Stratford CJ, Mould DJ, Mountford JO (2007) Hydrological science and wetland restoration: Some case studies from Europe. Hydrology and Earth System Sciences 11: 158–169. <ext-link xlink:href="10.5194/hess-11-158-2007" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-11-158-2007</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation>Arsénio P, Rodríguez‐González PM, Bernez IS, Dias F, Bugalho MN, Dufour S (2019) Riparian vegetation restoration: Does social perception reflect ecological value? River Research and Applications 36: 907–920. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1002/rra.3514" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/rra.3514</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation>Bednar-Friedl B, Biesbroek R, Schmidt DN, Alexander P, Børsheim KY, Carnicer J, Georgopoulou E, Haasnoot M, Le Cozannet G, Lionello P, Lipka O, Möllmann C, Muccione V, Mustonen T, Piepenburg D, Whitmarsh L (2022) Europe. In: Pörtner H-O, Roberts DC, Tignor M, Poloczanska ES, Mintenbeck K, Alegría A, Craig M, Langsdorf S, Löschke V, Möller V, Okem A, Rama B (Eds) Climate Change 2022: Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability. Contribution of Working Group II to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK, 1817–1927. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1017/9781009325844.015" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009325844.015</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation>Belletti B, Garcia de Leaniz C, Jones J, Bizzi S, Börger L, Segura G, Castelletti A, van de Bund W, Aarestrup K, Barry J, Belka K, Berkhuysen A, Birnie-Gauvin K, Bussettini M, Carolli M, Consuegra S, Dopico E, Feierfeil T, Fernández S, Fernandez Garrido P, Garcia-Vazquez E, Garrido S, Giannico G, Gough P, Jepsen N, Jones PE, Kemp P, Kerr J, King J, Łapińska M, Lázaro G, Lucas MC, Marcello L, Martin P, McGinnity P, O’Hanley J, Olivo del Amo R, Parasiewicz P, Pusch M, Rincon G, Rodriguez C, Royte J, Schneider CT, Tummers JS, Vallesi S, Vowles A, Verspoor E, Wanningen H, Wantzen KM, Wildman L, Zalewski M (2020) More than one million barriers fragment Europe’s rivers. Nature 588: 436–441. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-020-3005-2" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-3005-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation>Berezowski T, Wassen M, Szatyłowicz J, Chormański J, Ignar S, Batelaan O, Okruszko T (2018) Wetlands in flux: Looking for the drivers in a central European case. Wetlands Ecology and Management 26: 849–863. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s11273-018-9613-z" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11273-018-9613-z</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation>Bertassello LE, Basu NB, Maes J, Grizzetti B, La Notte A, Feyen L (2025) The important role of wetland conservation and restoration in nitrogen removal across European river basins. Nature Water 3: 867–880. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s44221-025-00465-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s44221-025-00465-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation>Birk S, Anzaldua G, Baattrup-Pedersen A, Bérczi-Siket A, Blackstock K, Buijse T, Carmen E, Carvalho L, Garcia X, Gerner N, Grondard N, Hernandez Herrero E, Ibrahim A, Kok S, Lenz M-I, Nyírő F, Okruszko T, Penning E, Pott L, Rouillard J, Schmidt-Kloiber A, Schwerk A, Sommerhäuser MM, St. John R, Waylen K, Hering D (2026) Building blocks for upscaling freshwater ecosystem restoration: Place-based strategies for a transdisciplinary challenge. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 261–287. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.148938" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.148938</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation>Blackbourn D (2007) The Conquest of Nature: Water, Landscape and the Making of Modern Germany. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation>BMU German Federal Ministry for the Environment, Nature Conservation and Nuclear Safety, Portuguese Ministry of Environment and Climate Action, Slovenian Ministry of the Environment and Spatial Planning (2020) Climate change and the European water dimension – Enhancing resilience. Background paper. Conference, 4–5 November 2020. adelphi, Fresh Thoughts Consulting GmbH, Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.fresh-thoughts.eu/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/water_climatechange_background_paper_bf.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fresh-thoughts.eu/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/water_climatechange_background_paper_bf.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation>Bullock A, Acreman M (2003) The role of wetlands in the hydrological cycle. Hydrology and Earth System Sciences 7: 358–389. <ext-link xlink:href="10.5194/hess-7-358-2003" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-7-358-2003</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation>Canal-Vergés P, Frederiksen L, Egemose S, Ebbensgaard T, Laustsen K, Flindt MR (2024) Impacts of Sea Level Rise on Danish Coastal Wetlands – a GIS-based Analysis. Environmental Management 75: 1039–1054. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s00267-024-02096-9" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00267-024-02096-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation>Capon SJ, Chambers LE, Mac Nally R, Naiman RJ, Davies P, Marshall N, Pittock J, Reid M, Capon T, Douglas M, Catford J, Baldwin DS, Stewardson M, Roberts J, Parsons M, Williams SE (2013) Riparian Ecosystems in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century: Hotspots for Climate Change Adaptation? Ecosystems (New York, N.Y.) 16: 359–381. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s10021-013-9656-1" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10021-013-9656-1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation>Carolli M, Garcia de Leaniz C, Jones J, Belletti B, Huđek H, Pusch M, Pandakov P, Börger L, van de Bund W (2023) Impacts of existing and planned hydropower dams on river fragmentation in the Balkan Region. The Science of the Total Environment 871: 161940. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.161940" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.161940</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation>Carrizo SF, Lengyel S, Kapusi F, Szabolcs M, Kasperidus HD, Scholz M, Markovic D, Freyhof J, Cid N, Cardoso AC, Darwall W (2017) Critical catchments for freshwater biodiversity conservation in Europe: identification, prioritisation and gap analysis. Arnott S (Ed.). Journal of Applied Ecology 54: 1209–1218. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/1365-2664.12842" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2664.12842</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation>Čížková H, Květ J, Comín FA, Laiho R, Pokorný J, Pithart D (2011) Actual state of European wetlands and their possible future in the context of global climate change. Aquatic Sciences 75: 3–26. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s00027-011-0233-4" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00027-011-0233-4</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation>Copernicus Global Drought Observatory (2024) Wetlands Drought Index. Factsheet. European Commission, Joint Research Centre. <ext-link xlink:href="https://drought.emergency.copernicus.eu/data/factsheets/factsheet_wetlandsDroughtIndex_gdo.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://drought.emergency.copernicus.eu/data/factsheets/factsheet_wetlandsDroughtIndex_gdo.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation>Copernicus Land Monitoring Service (2021) Riparian Zones: Land cover/land use and change 2012–2018 (Version 1) [Data set]. European Environment Agency. Retrieved from <ext-link xlink:href="https://land.copernicus.eu/en/products/riparian-zones" ext-link-type="uri">https://land.copernicus.eu/en/products/riparian-zones</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation>Cottet M, Piégay H, Bornette G (2013) Does human perception of wetland aesthetics and healthiness relate to ecological functioning? Journal of Environmental Management 128: 1012–1022. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.jenvman.2013.06.056" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2013.06.056</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation>Cvijanović D, Stammel B, Novković M, Adamescu M, Baumane M, Bonn A, Ehlert T, von Gönner J, Januschke K, Kaden US, Schipper C, Schulz-Zunkel C, Scholz M (2026) Towards effective and integrated riparian wetland monitoring in Europe: challenges and opportunities. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 121–148. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.167089" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.167089</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation>Davidson NC, van Dam AA, Finlayson CM, McInnes RJ (2019) Worth of wetlands: Revised global monetary values of coastal and inland wetland ecosystem services. Marine and Freshwater Research 70: 1189–1194. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1071/mf18391" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1071/mf18391</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation>Davidson NC, Dinesen L, Fennessy S, Finlayson CM, Grillas P, Grobicki A, McInnes RJ, Stroud DA (2020) Trends in the ecological character of the world’s wetlands. Marine and Freshwater Research 71: 127. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1071/mf18329" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1071/mf18329</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation>Day J, Anthony E, Costanza R, Edmonds D, Gunn J, Hopkinson C, Mann ME, Morris J, Osland M, Quirk T, Rovai A, Rybczyk J, Spencer T, Stephens J, Syvitski J, Twilley R, Visser J, White JR (2024) Coastal Wetlands in the Anthropocene. Annual Review of Environment and Resources 49: 105–135. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1146/annurev-environ-121922-041109" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-environ-121922-041109</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation>de Groot R, Brander L, van der Ploeg S, Costanza R, Bernard F, Braat L, Christie M, Crossman N, Ghermandi A, Hein L, Hussain S, Kumar P, McVittie A, Portela R, Rodriguez LC, ten Brink P, van Beukering P (2012) Global estimates of the value of ecosystems and their services in monetary units. Ecosystem Services 1: 50–61. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.ecoser.2012.07.005" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoser.2012.07.005</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation>De Knijf G, Billqvist M, van Grunsven R, Allen D, Assandri G, Bellotto V, Bruslund S, Bedjanič M, Conze K-J, Díaz Martínez C, Dolný A, Ferreira S, Garn A, Goertzen D, Holzinger W, Houard X, Hunger H, Jeanmougin M, Jović M, Kalniņš M, Karlsson T, Kazila E, Kitanova D, Kulijer D, Leus K, Lohr M, Maynou X, Motte G, Múrria C, Olsen K, Prunier F, Sahlén G, Schiel F-J, Šácha D, Šigutová H, Sparrow D, Sparrow R, Tańczuk A, Tarkowski A, Taylor P, Trottet A, Vilenica M, Vinko D, Lees C (2024) European Dragonflies: moving from assessment to conservation planning. Appendix to the Status Assessment of European Dragonflies (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Odonata</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) – European Red List of Dragonflies 2024. A report to the European Commission by the IUCN SSC Dragonfly Specialist Group and the IUCN SSC Conservation Planning Specialist Group. Conservation Planning Specialist Group. <ext-link xlink:href="https://inula.de/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/DeKnijf_et_al_2024_A2P_european_dragonflies.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://inula.de/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/DeKnijf_et_al_2024_A2P_european_dragonflies.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation>De la Cruz A, Numa C (2024) Habitat availability decline for waterbirds in a sensitive wetland: Climate change impact on the Ebro Delta. Ecological Modelling 498: 110896. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2024.110896" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2024.110896</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation>de la Vega-Leinert AC, Esteves LS, Andreu-Boussut V, Quinio L, Chadenas C, van Loon-Steensma JM, van den Hoven K (2026) Managed re-alignment: a multifaceted approach in ecological restoration of coastal floodplains. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 237–260. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.148691" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.148691</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation>Doody JP (2013) Coastal squeeze and managed realignment in southeast England, does it tell us anything about the future? Ocean andamp. Coastal Management 79: 34–41. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2012.05.008" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2012.05.008</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation>Dufour S, Urbanič G, Politti E (2020) Managers’ views on riparian vegetation management in France. Report, COST Action CA16208 CONVERGES, 13 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation>EC European Commission. Joint Research Centre. (2020a) Global warming and drought impacts in the EU: JRC PESETA IV project : Task 7. Publications Office, LU. <ext-link xlink:href="10.2760/597045" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2760/597045</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation>EC European Commission Joint Research Centre (2020b) Mapping and assessment of ecosystems and their services: an EU wide ecosystem assessment in support of the EU biodiversity strategy. Publications Office, LU. <ext-link xlink:href="10.2760/757183" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2760/757183</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation>EC European Commission (2021) Impact Assessment Accompanying the Proposal for a Regulation on Nature Restoration. SWD(2022) 167 final. Brussels, 2021. <ext-link xlink:href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/nature-restoration-law-impact-assessment_en" ext-link-type="uri">https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/nature-restoration-law-impact-assessment_en</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation>EC European Commission BISE Biodiversity Information System for Europe (2023) European habitats need to be restored - Wetlands. <ext-link xlink:href="https://biodiversity.europa.eu/europes-biodiversity/nature-restoration/habitats-to-be-restored/visualizations/habitat-condition-reported-for-wetlands" ext-link-type="uri">https://biodiversity.europa.eu/europes-biodiversity/nature-restoration/habitats-to-be-restored/visualizations/habitat-condition-reported-for-wetlands</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2018) Climate change and water - Warmer oceans, flooding and droughts. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/signals-archived/signals-2018-content-list/articles/climate-change-and-water-2014" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eea.europa.eu/signals-archived/signals-2018-content-list/articles/climate-change-and-water-2014</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2020a) Europe’s seas and coasts. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/themes/water/europes-seas-and-coasts/europes-seas-and-coasts" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eea.europa.eu/themes/water/europes-seas-and-coasts/europes-seas-and-coasts</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2020b) State of nature in the EU: results from reporting under the nature directives 2013 2018. Publications Office. <ext-link xlink:href="10.2800/705440" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2800/705440</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2021) Wet and dry – drought. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/europes-changing-climate-hazards-1/wet-and-dry-1/wet-and-dry-drought" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/europes-changing-climate-hazards-1/wet-and-dry-1/wet-and-dry-drought</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2024a) Europe’s changing climate hazards — an index-based interactive EEA report. What will the future bring when it comes to climate hazards? – Overview. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/europes-changing-climate-hazards-1/what-will-the-future-bring" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/europes-changing-climate-hazards-1/what-will-the-future-bring</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation>EEA European Environment Agency (2024b) Europe’s state of water 2024: the need for improved water resilience. Publications Office, LU. <ext-link xlink:href="10.2800/02236" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2800/02236</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation>Englund O, Börjesson P, Mola-Yudego B, Berndes G, Dimitriou I, Cederberg C, Scarlat N (2021) Strategic deployment of riparian buffers and windbreaks in Europe can co-deliver biomass and environmental benefits. Communications Earth &amp;amp. Environment 2: 176. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s43247-021-00247-y" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00247-y</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation>Erwin KL (2008) Wetlands and global climate change: The role of wetland restoration in a changing world. Wetlands Ecology and Management 17: 71–84. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s11273-008-9119-1" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11273-008-9119-1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation>EU/92/43/EEC (1992) Council Directive 92/43/EEC of 21 May 1992 on the conservation of natural habitats and of wild fauna and flora. <ext-link xlink:href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01992L0043-20130701" ext-link-type="uri">https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A01992L0043-20130701</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation>Feld CK, Fernandes MR, Ferreira MT, Hering D, Ormerod SJ, Venohr M, Gutiérrez-Cánovas C (2018) Evaluating riparian solutions to multiple stressor problems in river ecosystems — A conceptual study. Water Research 139: 381–394. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.watres.2018.04.014" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2018.04.014</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation>Ferreira CSS, Kašanin-Grubin M, Solomun MK, Sushkova S, Minkina T, Zhao W, Kalantari Z (2023) Wetlands as nature-based solutions for water management in different environments. Current Opinion in Environmental Science &amp;amp. Health 33: 100476. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.coesh.2023.100476" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coesh.2023.100476</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation>Fink S, Kräuchi N, Stofer S, Weber A, Horchler PJ (2026) Conservation planning for riverine biodiversity under changing climate: use of models. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 47–62. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.149645" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.149645</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation>FitzGerald DM, Fenster MS, Argow BA, Buynevich IV (2008) Coastal Impacts Due to Sea-Level Rise. Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences 36: 601–647. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1146/annurev.earth.35.031306.140139" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.earth.35.031306.140139</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation>Fluet-Chouinard E, Stocker BD, Zhang Z, Malhotra A, Melton JR, Poulter B, Kaplan JO, Goldewijk KK, Siebert S, Minayeva T, Hugelius G, Joosten H, Barthelmes A, Prigent C, Aires F, Hoyt AM, Davidson N, Finlayson CM, Lehner B, Jackson RB, McIntyre PB (2023) Extensive global wetland loss over the past three centuries. Nature 614: 281–286. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-022-05572-6" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-05572-6</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation>Fuller MR, Leinenbach P, Detenbeck NE, Labiosa R, Isaak DJ (2022) Riparian vegetation shade restoration and loss effects on recent and future stream temperatures. Restoration Ecology 30(7): e13626. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/rec.13626" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/rec.13626</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <mixed-citation>Giersbergen Q, Barthelmes A, Couwenberg J, Fritz C, Lång K, Martin N, Tanneberger F (2024) Identifying hotspots of greenhouse gas emissions from drained peatlands in the European Union. <ext-link xlink:href="10.21203/rs.3.rs-4629642/v1" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-4629642/v1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <mixed-citation>Glaubrecht M (2025) Das stille Sterben der Natur: Wie wir die Artenvielfalt und uns selbst retten [The Silent Death of Nature: How We Can Save Biodiversity and Ourselves]. C. Bertelsmann, 224 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <mixed-citation>Globevnik L, Januschke K, Kail J, Snoj L, et al. (2020) Preliminary assessment of river floodplain condition in Europe (Report no. 5/2020).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <mixed-citation>Gopal B (2009) Biodiversity in wetlands. The wetlands handbook 2: 65–95. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1002/9781444315813.ch3" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/9781444315813.ch3</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <mixed-citation>Granata F, Di Nunno F (2025) Pathways for Hydrological Resilience: Strategies for Adaptation in a Changing Climate. Earth Systems and Environment. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s41748-024-00567-x" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s41748-024-00567-x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <mixed-citation>Grill G, Lehner B, Thieme M, Geenen B, Tickner D, Antonelli F, Babu S, Borrelli P, Cheng L, Crochetiere H, Ehalt Macedo H, Filgueiras R, Goichot M, Higgins J, Hogan Z, Lip B, McClain ME, Meng J, Mulligan M, Nilsson C, Olden JD, Opperman JJ, Petry P, Reidy Liermann C, Sáenz L, Salinas-Rodríguez S, Schelle P, Schmitt RJP, Snider J, Tan F, Tockner K, Valdujo PH, van Soesbergen A, Zarfl C (2019) Mapping the world’s free-flowing rivers. Nature 569: 215–221. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-019-1111-9" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1111-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <mixed-citation>Harenda KM, Lamentowicz M, Samson M, Chojnicki BH (2017) The Role of Peatlands and Their Carbon Storage Function in the Context of Climate Change. GeoPlanet: Earth and Planetary Sciences, 169–187. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/978-3-319-71788-3_12" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-71788-3_12</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B57">
        <mixed-citation>Harris RMB, Beaumont LJ, Vance TR, Tozer CR, Remenyi TA, Perkins-Kirkpatrick SE, Mitchell PJ, Nicotra AB, McGregor S, Andrew NR, Letnic M, Kearney MR, Wernberg T, Hutley LB, Chambers LE, Fletcher M-S, Keatley MR, Woodward CA, Williamson G, Duke NC, Bowman DMJS (2018) Biological responses to the press and pulse of climate trends and extreme events. Nature Climate Change 8: 579–587. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41558-018-0187-9" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-018-0187-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B58">
        <mixed-citation>Hering D, Schürings C, Wenskus F, Blackstock K, Borja A, Birk S, Bullock C, Carvalho L, Dagher-Kharrat MB, Lakner S, Lovrić N, McGuinness S, Nabuurs G-J, Sánchez-Arcilla A, Settele J, Pe’er G (2023) Securing success for the Nature Restoration Law. Science 382: 1248–1250. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1126/science.adk1658" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.adk1658</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B59">
        <mixed-citation>Hobbs RJ, Arico S, Aronson J, Baron JS, Bridgewater P, Cramer VA, Epstein PR, Ewel JJ, Klink CA, Lugo AE, Norton D, Ojima D, Richardson DM, Sanderson EW, Valladares F, Vilà M, Zamora R, Zobel M (2006) Novel ecosystems: Theoretical and management aspects of the new ecological world order. Global Ecology and Biogeography 15: 1–7. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/j.1466-822x.2006.00212.x" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1466-822x.2006.00212.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B60">
        <mixed-citation>Hohensinner S, Sonnlechner C, Schmid M, Winiwarter V (2013) Two steps back, one step forward: Reconstructing the dynamic Danube riverscape under human influence in Vienna. Water History 5: 121–143. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s12685-013-0076-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12685-013-0076-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B61">
        <mixed-citation>Hu S, Niu Z, Chen Y, Li L, Zhang H (2017) Global wetlands: Potential distribution, wetland loss, and status. The Science of the Total Environment 586: 319–327. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.02.001" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.02.001</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B62">
        <mixed-citation>Ibáñez C, Caiola N, Elphick CS, Grillas P (2026) To what extent is coastal wetland biodiversity endangered by climate change? How can we boost the resilience of coastal ecosystems? In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 63–94. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.154795" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.154795</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B63">
        <mixed-citation>Ilg C, Dziock F, Foeckler F, Follner K, Gerisch M, Glaeser J, Rink A, Schanowski A, Scholz M, Deichner O, Henle K (2008) Long‐Term Reactions of Plants and Macroinvertebrates to extreme Floods In Floodplain Grasslands. Ecology 89: 2392–2398. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1890/08-0528.1" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1890/08-0528.1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B64">
        <mixed-citation>IPBES Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (2019) Global Assessment Report on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services of the Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services. Díaz S, Settele J, Brondízio ES, et al. (Eds). IPBES Secretariat, Bonn, Germany, 1148 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.3831673" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3831673</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B65">
        <mixed-citation>IPCC Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) (2023a) Climate Change 2021 – The Physical Science Basis. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1017/9781009157896" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009157896</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B66">
        <mixed-citation>IPCC Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (2023b) Climate Change 2022 – Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1017/9781009325844" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009325844</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B67">
        <mixed-citation>IPCC Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (2023c) Sixth Assessment Report (AR6). IPCC, Geneva, Switzerland. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/report/sixth-assessment-report-cycle/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/report/sixth-assessment-report-cycle/</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B68">
        <mixed-citation>Jähnig SC, Carolli M, Dehnhardt A, Jardine T, Podschun S, Pusch M, Scholz M, Tharme RE, Wantzen KM, Langhans SD (2022) Ecosystem Services of River Systems – Irreplaceable, Undervalued, and at Risk. Encyclopedia of Inland Waters: 424–435. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/b978-0-12-819166-8.00129-8" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-819166-8.00129-8</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B69">
        <mixed-citation>Januschke K, Hering D, Stammel B, Brunzel S, Scholz M, Rumm A, Sattler J, Fischer-Bedtke C, Makiej A, Foeckler F (2023) Biozönotische Erfolgskontrolle von Renaturierungsmaßnahmen an Gewässerufern und in Auen: Typologische Grundlagen und Bewertungsverfahren. BfN-Schriften 655. Bundesamt für Naturschutz (BfN), Bonn, 201 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="10.19217/skr655" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.19217/skr655</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B70">
        <mixed-citation>Jay M, Plieninger T (2025) Addressing landscape multifunctionality in conservation and restoration. Nature Reviews Biodiversity 1: 717–732. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s44358-025-00091-4" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s44358-025-00091-4</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B71">
        <mixed-citation>Junk WJ, Brown M, Campbell IC, Finlayson M, Gopal B, Ramberg L, Warner BG (2006) The comparative biodiversity of seven globally important wetlands: A synthesis. Aquatic Sciences 68: 400–414. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s00027-006-0856-z" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00027-006-0856-z</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B72">
        <mixed-citation>Junk WJ, An S, Finlayson CM, Gopal B, Květ J, Mitchell SA, Mitsch WJ, Robarts RD (2012) Current state of knowledge regarding the world’s wetlands and their future under global climate change: A synthesis. Aquatic Sciences 75: 151–167. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s00027-012-0278-z" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00027-012-0278-z</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B73">
        <mixed-citation>Kaden US, Scholz M, Buijse AD, Cvijanović D, Froese I, Diack I, Duffield S, Ibáñez C, Jähnig SC, Januschke K, Ludewig K, Marsden K, Müller P, Rodríguez-González PM, Schulz-Zunkel C, Stadler J, Stammel B, Wantzen KM, Weber A, Wulf S, Zak D, Bonn A (2023) Riverine and coastal wetlands in Europe for biodiversity and climate. State of knowledge, challenges and opportunities. BfN Discussion paper. Bundesamt für Naturschutz (BfN), Bonn, 1–44. <ext-link xlink:href="10.19217/hgr233en" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.19217/hgr233en</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B74">
        <mixed-citation>Keddy PA (2010) Wetland Ecology, 476–497. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1017/cbo9780511778179" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1017/cbo9780511778179</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B75">
        <mixed-citation>Klijn F, Asselman N, Wagenaar D (2018) Room for Rivers: Risk Reduction by Enhancing the Flood Conveyance Capacity of The Netherlands’ Large Rivers. Geosciences 8: 224. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3390/geosciences8060224" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/geosciences8060224</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B76">
        <mixed-citation>Klusmann C, Brotherton P, Schiller T, Wulf S, Marsden K (2026) Wetlands in the EU policy context. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 317–335. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.163780" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.163780</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B77">
        <mixed-citation>Kmetova-Biro E, Rožac V, Frank G, Marušić M, Lagutov V (2026) Bridging protected areas along the Danube. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 217–236. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.160887" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.160887</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B78">
        <mixed-citation>Koenzen U, Burkhardt J, Jegel S, Kappenberg A, Katzmann D, Neuschulz M, Peintinger M, Scholz M, Schury M (2021) Status Report on Floodplains 2021 – Floodplains in Germany. Federal Ministry for the Environment, Nature Conservation and Nuclear Safety (BMU) &amp; Federal Agency for Nature Conservation (BfN), 71 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B79">
        <mixed-citation>Ludewig K, Shupe HA, Vásconez Navas LK, Mueller P, Nolte S, Hunt CA (2026) Case studies from Germany and Scotland indicate climate change mitigation potential of riverine and coastal wetlands. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 149–173. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.153910" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.153910</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B80">
        <mixed-citation>Macháč J, Zaňková L, Hekrle M, Scholz M (2026) Nature-based solutions with sponge functions: socio-economic importance and valuation. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 289–315. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.164530" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.164530</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B81">
        <mixed-citation>Maltby E [Ed.] (2009) Functional assessment of wetlands: towards evaluation of ecosystem services. Elsevier. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1201/9781439829141" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1201/9781439829141</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B82">
        <mixed-citation>Marchi M, Castellanos-Acuña D, Hamann A, Wang T, Ray D, Menzel A (2020) ClimateEU, scale-free climate normals, historical time series, and future projections for Europe. Scientific Data 7: 428. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41597-020-00763-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-00763-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B83">
        <mixed-citation>Martínez-Megías C, Rico A (2022) Biodiversity impacts by multiple anthropogenic stressors in Mediterranean coastal wetlands. The Science of the Total Environment 818: 151712. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151712" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.151712</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B84">
        <mixed-citation>McGranahan G, Balk D, Anderson B (2007) The rising tide: Assessing the risks of climate change and human settlements in low elevation coastal zones. Environment and Urbanization 19: 17–37. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1177/0956247807076960" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1177/0956247807076960</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B85">
        <mixed-citation>MedECC (2020) Climate and Environmental Change in the Mediterranean Basin – Current Situation and Risks for the Future. First Mediterranean Assessment Report. Zenodo, 632 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="10.5281/ZENODO.4768833" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.4768833</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B86">
        <mixed-citation>Meli P, Rey Benayas JM, Balvanera P, Martínez Ramos M (2014) Restoration Enhances Wetland Biodiversity and Ecosystem Service Supply, but Results Are Context-Dependent: A Meta-Analysis. PLoS ONE 9: e93507. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0093507" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0093507</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B87">
        <mixed-citation>MEA Millennium Ecosystem Assessment (2005) Ecosystems and human well-being: wetlands and water synthesis. World Resources Institute, Washington, DC. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.millenniumassessment.org/documents/document.356.aspx.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.millenniumassessment.org/documents/document.356.aspx.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B88">
        <mixed-citation>Mitsch WJ, Bernal B, Nahlik AM, Mander Ü, Zhang L, Anderson CJ, Jørgensen SE, Brix H (2012) Wetlands, carbon, and climate change. Landscape Ecology 28: 583–597. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s10980-012-9758-8" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10980-012-9758-8</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B89">
        <mixed-citation>Möller I, Kudella M, Rupprecht F, Spencer T, Paul M, van Wesenbeeck BK, Wolters G, Jensen K, Bouma TJ, Miranda-Lange M, Schimmels S (2014) Wave attenuation over coastal salt marshes under storm surge conditions. Nature Geoscience 7: 727–731. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/ngeo2251" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/ngeo2251</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B90">
        <mixed-citation>Moomaw WR, Chmura GL, Davies GT, Finlayson CM, Middleton BA, Natali SM, Perry JE, Roulet N, Sutton-Grier AE (2018) Wetlands In a Changing Climate: Science, Policy and Management. Wetlands 38: 183–205. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s13157-018-1023-8" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13157-018-1023-8</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B91">
        <mixed-citation>Neubauer SC, Megonigal JP (2015) Moving Beyond Global Warming Potentials to Quantify the Climatic Role of Ecosystems. Ecosystems (New York, N.Y.) 18: 1000–1013. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s10021-015-9879-4" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10021-015-9879-4</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B92">
        <mixed-citation>Nivet C, Frazier S (2004) A review of European wetland inventory information. In: Taylor ARD, van Eerden M (eds) Wetlands International (Ramsar). Report prepared in the framework of “A pilot study towards a Pan-European wetland inventory”.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B93">
        <mixed-citation>Okruszko T, Duel H, Acreman M, Grygoruk M, Flörke M, Schneider C (2011) Broad-scale ecosystem services of European wetlands—overview of the current situation and future perspectives under different climate and water management scenarios. Hydrological Sciences Journal 56: 1501–1517. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1080/02626667.2011.631188" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/02626667.2011.631188</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B94">
        <mixed-citation>Petts GE (1987) River regulation in Europe: An historical perspective. Regulated Rivers 1(4): 363–369.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B95">
        <mixed-citation>Pröbstl F, Zinngrebe Y, Böcher M, Schmid S, Scholz M, Stammel B, Hüesker F (2025) Living with the incoherent: Practical insights on implementing European restoration policies for biodiversity policy integration. Ambio 54: 1635–1647. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s13280-025-02180-2" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-025-02180-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B96">
        <mixed-citation>Ramey TL, Richardson JS (2017) Terrestrial Invertebrates in the Riparian Zone: Mechanisms Underlying Their Unique Diversity. Bioscience 67: 808–819. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1093/biosci/bix078" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/bix078</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B97">
        <mixed-citation>Ramsar Convention (1971) Convention on wetlands of international importance especially as waterfowl habitat. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ramsar.org/sites/default/files/documents/library/current_convention_text_e.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ramsar.org/sites/default/files/documents/library/current_convention_text_e.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B98">
        <mixed-citation>Ramsar Convention on Wetlands (2018) Global wetland outlook: State of the world’s wetlands and their services to people 2018. Ramsar Convention Secretariat, Gland, Switzerland, 1–89. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=3261606" ext-link-type="uri">https://ssrn.com/abstract=3261606</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B99">
        <mixed-citation>Ramsar Convention on Wetlands (2021a) Global Wetland Outlook: Special Edition 2021. Gland, Switzerland: Secretariat of the Convention on Wetlands. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ramsar.org/resources/publications/global-wetland-outlook" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ramsar.org/resources/publications/global-wetland-outlook</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B100">
        <mixed-citation>Ramsar Convention on Wetlands (2021b) Wetlands and biodiversity. Ramsar Convention Secretariat, Gland, Switzerland. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ramsar.org/sites/default/files/ramsar_50_factsheet_biodiversity_english_as_v7.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ramsar.org/sites/default/files/ramsar_50_factsheet_biodiversity_english_as_v7.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B101">
        <mixed-citation>Reimold RJ, Phillips JH, Hardisky MA (1980) Socio-cultural values of wetlands. Estuarine Perspectives: 79–89. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/b978-0-12-404060-1.50015-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-404060-1.50015-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B102">
        <mixed-citation>Renöfält BM, Jansson R, Nilsson C (2009) Effects of hydropower generation and opportunities for environmental flow management in Swedish riverine ecosystems. Freshwater Biology 55: 49–67. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-2427.2009.02241.x" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2427.2009.02241.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B103">
        <mixed-citation>Rodríguez‐González PM, Abraham E, Aguiar F, Andreoli A, Baležentienė L, Berisha N, Bernez I, Bruen M, Bruno D, Camporeale C, Čarni A, Chilikova‐Lubomirova M, Corenblit D, Ćušterevska R, Doody T, England J, Evette A, Francis R, Garófano‐Gómez V, González del Tánago M, Gultekin YS, Guyard F, Hellsten S, Hinkov G, Jakubínský J, Janssen P, Jansson R, Kail J, Keles E, Kelly‐Quinn M, Kidová A, Kiss T, Kulvik M, La Porta N, Laslier M, Latella M, Lorenz S, Mandžukovski D, Manolaki P, Martinez‐Fernández V, Merritt D, Michez A, Milovanović J, Okruszko T, Papastergiadou E, Penning E, Pielech R, Politti E, Portela A, Riis T, Škvorc Ž, Slezák M, Stammel B, Stella J, Stesevic D, Stupar V, Tammeorg O, Tammeorg P, Fosholt TM, Urbanič G, Villar M, Vogiatzakis I, Vrchovsky P, Yousefpour R, Zinke P, Zlatanov T, Dufour S (2022) Bringing the margin to the focus: 10 challenges for riparian vegetation science and management. WIREs. Water 9. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1002/wat2.1604" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/wat2.1604</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B104">
        <mixed-citation>Rouillard J, Meier J, Blackstock KL, Matthews KB, Birk S (2026) Does the Common Agricultural Policy 2023–2027 support the restoration of freshwater ecosystems? In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 337–354. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.148845" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.148845</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B105">
        <mixed-citation>Sabo JL, Sponseller R, Dixon M, Gade K, Harms T, Heffernan J, Jani A, Katz G, Soykan C, Watts J, Welter J (2005) Riparian Zones Increase Regional Species Richness By Harbouring Different, Not More, Species. Ecology 86: 56–62. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1890/04-0668" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1890/04-0668</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B106">
        <mixed-citation>Salimi S, Almuktar SAAAN, Scholz M (2021) Impact of climate change on wetland ecosystems: A critical review of experimental wetlands. Journal of Environmental Management 286: 112160. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.112160" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.112160</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B107">
        <mixed-citation>Schindler S, O’Neill FH, Biró M, Damm C, Gasso V, Kanka R, van der Sluis T, Krug A, Lauwaars SG, Sebesvari Z, Pusch M, Baranovsky B, Ehlert T, Neukirchen B, Martin JR, Euller K, Mauerhofer V, Wrbka T (2016) Multifunctional floodplain management and biodiversity effects: A knowledge synthesis for six European countries. Biodiversity and Conservation 25: 1349–1382. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s10531-016-1129-3" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10531-016-1129-3</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B108">
        <mixed-citation>Schleupner C (2011) Modelling the Implications of Climate Change for European Freshwater Wetland Distributions: A Review of Knowledge and Gaps. The International Journal of Climate Change: Impacts and Responses 2: 37–62. <ext-link xlink:href="10.18848/1835-7156/cgp/v02i03/37073" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.18848/1835-7156/cgp/v02i03/37073</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B109">
        <mixed-citation>Schneider C, Flörke M, Geerling G, Duel H, Grygoruk M, Okruszko T (2011) The future of European floodplain wetlands under a changing climate. Journal of Water and Climate Change 2: 106–122. <ext-link xlink:href="10.2166/wcc.2011.020" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2166/wcc.2011.020</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B110">
        <mixed-citation>Schuerch M, Spencer T, Temmerman S, Kirwan ML, Wolff C, Lincke D, McOwen CJ, Pickering MD, Reef R, Vafeidis AT, Hinkel J, Nicholls RJ, Brown S (2018) Future response of global coastal wetlands to sea-level rise. Nature 561: 231–234. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-018-0476-5" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-018-0476-5</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B111">
        <mixed-citation>Serra-Llobet A, Jähnig SC, Geist J, Kondolf GM, Damm C, Scholz M, Lund J, Opperman JJ, Yarnell SM, Pawley A, Shader E, Cain J, Zingraff-Hamed A, Grantham TE, Eisenstein W, Schmitt R (2022) Restoring Rivers and Floodplains for Habitat and Flood Risk Reduction: Experiences in Multi-Benefit Floodplain Management From California and Germany. Frontiers in Environmental Science 9: 778568. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3389/fenvs.2021.778568" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3389/fenvs.2021.778568</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B112">
        <mixed-citation>Spencer T, Schuerch M, Nicholls RJ, Hinkel J, Lincke D, Vafeidis AT, Reef R, McFadden L, Brown S (2016) Global coastal wetland change under sea-level rise and related stresses: The DIVA Wetland Change Model. Global and Planetary Change 139: 15–30. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.gloplacha.2015.12.018" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2015.12.018</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B113">
        <mixed-citation>Spinoni J, Vogt JV, Naumann G, Barbosa P, Dosio A (2017) Will drought events become more frequent and severe in Europe? International Journal of Climatology 38: 1718–1736. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1002/joc.5291" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.5291</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B114">
        <mixed-citation>Stammel B, Jähnig SC, Mehl D, Pusch M, Srđević Z, Tschikof M, Wulf S, Scholz M (2026) Assessing ecosystem services across scales to support nature-based solutions in river floodplains: a review of non-monetary tools. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 95–119. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.148716" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.148716</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B115">
        <mixed-citation>Stella JC, Bendix J (2019) Multiple Stressors in Riparian Ecosystems. Multiple Stressors in River Ecosystems, 81–110. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/b978-0-12-811713-2.00005-4" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-811713-2.00005-4</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B116">
        <mixed-citation>Stoffers T, Schultze A-K, Ehlert T, Kaiser L, Scholz M, Nagelkerke LAJ (2026) Challenges and opportunities in restoring European free-flowing rivers. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 355–381. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.173762" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.173762</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B117">
        <mixed-citation>Tabacchi E, Tabacchi AP (2007) Functional Significance of Species Composition Riparian Plan Communities. Journal of the American Water Resources Association 37: 1629–1637. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/j.1752-1688.2001.tb03665.x" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1752-1688.2001.tb03665.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B118">
        <mixed-citation>Taillardat P, Thompson BS, Garneau M, Trottier K, Friess DA (2020) Climate change mitigation potential of wetlands and the cost-effectiveness of their restoration. Interface Focus 10: 20190129. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1098/rsfs.2019.0129" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1098/rsfs.2019.0129</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B119">
        <mixed-citation>Tanneberger F, Tegetmeyer C, Busse S, Barthelmes A, Associates (2017) The peatland map of Europe. Mires and Peat: 1–17. <ext-link xlink:href="10.19189/MaP.2016.OMB.264" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.19189/MaP.2016.OMB.264</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B120">
        <mixed-citation>Tanneberger F, Moen A, Barthelmes A, Lewis E, Miles L, Sirin A, Tegetmeyer C, Joosten H (2021) Mires in Europe—Regional Diversity, Condition and Protection. Diversity 13: 381. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3390/d13080381" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/d13080381</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B121">
        <mixed-citation>Tegetmeyer C, Kaiser M, Barthelmes A (2024) European Wetland Map (EWM): Technical Description and Data Sources. Greifswald Mire Centre. <ext-link xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/14745285/files/EWM24_Technical_description_GMC.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/records/14745285/files/EWM24_Technical_description_GMC.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B122">
        <mixed-citation>Tegetmeyer C, Kaiser M, Barthelmes A (2025) The European Wetland Map (‘EWM’). [Data set]. Zenodo. <ext-link xlink:href="10.5281/ZENODO.15302184" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15302184</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B123">
        <mixed-citation>Thiere G, Milenkovski S, Lindgren P-E, Sahlén G, Berglund O, Weisner SEB (2009) Wetland creation in agricultural landscapes: Biodiversity benefits on local and regional scales. Biological Conservation 142: 964–973. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.biocon.2009.01.006" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2009.01.006</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B124">
        <mixed-citation>Tockner K, Malard F, Ward JV (2000) An extension of the flood pulse concept. Hydrological Processes 14: 2861–2883. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/1099-1085(200011/12)14:16/17%3C2861::aid-hyp124%3E3.0.co;2-f">https://doi.org/10.1002/1099-1085(200011/12)14:16/17&lt;2861::aid-hyp124&gt;3.0.co;2-f</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B125">
        <mixed-citation>Tockner K, Zarfl C, Robinson CT [Eds] (2022) Rivers of Europe (2<sup>nd</sup> edn.). Elsevier, 924 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/c2017-0-03745-x" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/c2017-0-03745-x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B126">
        <mixed-citation>Turetsky MR, Abbott BW, Jones MC, Anthony KW, Olefeldt D, Schuur EAG, Grosse G, Kuhry P, Hugelius G, Koven C, Lawrence DM, Gibson C, Sannel ABK, McGuire AD (2020) Carbon release through abrupt permafrost thaw. Nature Geoscience 13: 138–143. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s41561-019-0526-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-019-0526-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B127">
        <mixed-citation>UNFCC (2018) Wetlands Disappearing Three Times Faster than Forests. <ext-link xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/news/wetlands-disappearingthree-times-faster-than-forests" ext-link-type="uri">https://unfccc.int/news/wetlands-disappearingthree-times-faster-than-forests</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B128">
        <mixed-citation>Urbanič G, Politti E, Rodríguez-González PM, Payne R, Schook D, Alves MH, Anđelković A, Bruno D, Chilikova-Lubomirova M, Di Lonardo S, Egozi R, Garófano-Gómez V, Gomes Marques I, González del Tánago M, Gültekin YS, Gumiero B, Hellsten S, Hinkov G, Jakubínský J, Janssen P, Jansson R, Kelly-Quinn M, Kiss T, Lorenz S, Martinez Romero R, Mihaljević Z, Papastergiadou E, Pavlin Urbanič M, Penning E, Riis T, Šibík J, Šibíková M, Zlatanov T, Dufour S (2022) Riparian Zones—From Policy Neglected to Policy Integrated. Frontiers in Environmental Science 10: 868527. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3389/fenvs.2022.868527" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3389/fenvs.2022.868527</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B129">
        <mixed-citation>Vanneuville W, Wolters H, Scholz M, Werner B, Uhel R, Snoj L, Globevnik L, Mysiak J, Seijger C, Schulz-Zunkel C (2016) Flood risks and environmental vulnerability: Exploring the synergies between floodplain restoration, water policies and thematic policies. EEA Report 1/2016. Office for Official Publications of the European Communities, Luxembourg, 78 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B130">
        <mixed-citation>Verhoeven JTA (2014) Wetlands in Europe: Perspectives for restoration of a lost paradise. Ecological Engineering 66: 6–9. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.ecoleng.2013.03.006" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoleng.2013.03.006</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B131">
        <mixed-citation>Verniest F, Galewski T, Boutron O, Dami L, Defos du Rau P, Guelmami A, Julliard R, Popoff N, Suet M, Willm L, Abdou W, Azafzaf H, Bendjedda N, Bino T, Borg JJ, Božič L, Dakki M, Hamoumi RE, Encarnação V, Erciyas‐Yavuz K, Etayeb K, Georgiev V, Hamada A, Hatzofe O, Ieronymidou C, Langendoen T, Mikuska T, Molina B, Moniz F, Moussy C, Ouassou A, Petkov N, Portolou D, Qaneer T, Sayoud S, Šćiban M, Topić G, Uzunova D, Vine G, Vizi A, Xeka E, Zenatello M, Gaget E, Viol IL (2024) Exposure of wetlands important for nonbreeding waterbirds to sea‐level rise in the Mediterranean. Conservation Biology : The Journal of the Society for Conservation Biology 38(6): e14288. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1111/cobi.14288" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.14288</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B132">
        <mixed-citation>von Unger M, Tonneijck FH, Soto C (2022) Voluntary Carbon Markets for Wetland Conservation and Restoration. Wetlands International, Ede, The Netherlands, 32 pp. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wetlands.org/download/5519/?tmstv=1750939131" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wetlands.org/download/5519/?tmstv=1750939131</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B133">
        <mixed-citation>Wang F, Sanders CJ, Santos IR, Tang J, Schuerch M, Kirwan ML, Kopp RE, Zhu K, Li X, Yuan J, Liu W, Li Z (2020) Global blue carbon accumulation in tidal wetlands increases with climate change. National Science Review 8(9): nwaa296. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1093/nsr/nwaa296" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1093/nsr/nwaa296</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B134">
        <mixed-citation>Wantzen KM, Cao Y (2026) Cultural practices in European riverine floodplains: formation, typology, co-decline of biocultural diversity, and emerging drivers of conservation and sustainable management. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 195–215. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.156771" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.156771</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B135">
        <mixed-citation>Weissteiner C, Ickerott M, Ott H, Probeck M, Ramminger G, Clerici N, Dufourmont H, de Sousa A (2016) Europe’s Green Arteries - A Continental Dataset of Riparian Zones. Remote Sensing 8: 925. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3390/rs8110925" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/rs8110925</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B136">
        <mixed-citation>Were D, Kansiime F, Fetahi T, Cooper A, Jjuuko C (2019) Carbon Sequestration by Wetlands: A Critical Review of Enhancement Measures for Climate Change Mitigation. Earth Systems and Environment 3: 327–340. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1007/s41748-019-00094-0" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s41748-019-00094-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B137">
        <mixed-citation>Wetlands International (2020) Ensuring the global biodiversity framework prioritises measures to safeguard wetlands and wetland biodiversity. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wetlands.org/download/5507/?tmstv=1747746227" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wetlands.org/download/5507/?tmstv=1747746227</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B138">
        <mixed-citation>Wetlands International (2022) Wetland services for adaptation: Wetlands and climate change adaptation. Sustaining and restoring wetlands: an effective climate change response. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wetlands.org/publications/wetlands-and-climate-change-adaptation-brochure-2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wetlands.org/publications/wetlands-and-climate-change-adaptation-brochure-2/</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B139">
        <mixed-citation>Wetlands International (2025) Wetland biodiversity in Europe. <ext-link xlink:href="https://europe.wetlands.org/home-2/our-work/wetland-biodiversity/?utm_" ext-link-type="uri">https://europe.wetlands.org/home-2/our-work/wetland-biodiversity/?utm_</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B140">
        <mixed-citation>Wood KA, Jupe LL, Aguiar FC, Collins AM, Davidson SJ, Freeman W, Kirkpatrick L, Lobato-de Magalhães T, McKinley E, Nuno A, Pagès JF, Petruzzella A, Pritchard D, Reeves JP, Thomaz SM, Thornton SA, Yamashita H, Newth JL (2024) A global systematic review of the cultural ecosystem services provided by wetlands. Ecosystem Services 70: 101673. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.ecoser.2024.101673" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoser.2024.101673</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B141">
        <mixed-citation>Xiong Y, Mo S, Wu H, Qu X, Liu Y, Zhou L (2023) Influence of human activities and climate change on wetland landscape pattern - A review. The Science of the Total Environment 879: 163112. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163112" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163112</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B142">
        <mixed-citation>Zak D, Tschikof M, Natho S, Jes Petersen R, Kronvang B, Hoffmann CC, Liu H, Wang M, Kaden US (2026) Floodplains and coastal wetlands as nutrient sinks: a restoration perspective. In: Kaden US, Schmid S, Wulf S, Marsden K, Klusmann C, Bonn A, Tockner K, Scholz M (Eds) Wetlands in a Changing Climate: Restoring Coasts and Floodplains. Nature Conservation 62: 175–193. <ext-link xlink:href="10.3897/natureconservation.62.158302" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3897/natureconservation.62.158302</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B143">
        <mixed-citation>Zedler JB, Kercher S (2005) WETLAND RESOURCES: Status, Trends, Ecosystem Services, and Restorability. Annual Review of Environment and Resources 30: 39–74. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1146/annurev.energy.30.050504.144248" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.energy.30.050504.144248</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B144">
        <mixed-citation>Zinke L (2020) The colours of carbon. Nature Reviews Earth &amp; Environment 1: 1–141. <ext-link xlink:href="10.1038/s43017-020-0037-y" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-020-0037-y</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <app-group>
      <app id="app1">
        <title>Appendix 1</title>
        <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table A1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>List of habitat types (Annex I of the European Habitats Directive 92/43/EEC, reporting period 2013–2018) relevant to riverine and coastal wetlands, considered for the analyses in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Box 2</xref>. The selection is based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B129">Vanneuville et al. (2016)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Januschke et al. (2023)</xref>, and expert knowledge.</p>
          </caption>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>EU wetland habitat type code</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>EU wetland habitat type</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>1</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Coastal Habitats</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1110</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sandbanks which are slightly covered by sea water all the time</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1120</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Posidonia">Posidonia</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> beds (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Posidonion">Posidonion</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="oceanicae">oceanicae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1130</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estuaries</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1140</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mudflats and sandflats</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1150*</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coastal lagoons</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1160</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large shallow inlets and bays</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1170</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reefs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1210</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual vegetation of drift lines</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial vegetation of stony banks</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1230</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetated sea cliffs of the Atlantic and Baltic Coasts</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1240</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetated sea cliffs of the Mediterranean coasts with endemic <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Limonium">Limonium</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> spp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1250</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetated sea cliffs with endemic flora of the Macaronesian coasts</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1310</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salicornia">Salicornia</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and other annuals colonizing mud and sand</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1320</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Spartina">Spartina</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> swards (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Spartinion">Spartinion</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="maritimae">maritimae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1420</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atlantic salt meadows (<italic>Glauco-Puccinellietalia maritimae</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1340</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inland salt meadows</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1410</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean salt meadows (<italic>Juncetalia maritimi</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1420</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean and thermo-Atlantic halophilous scrubs (<italic>Sarcocornetea fruticosi</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1430</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Halo-nitrophilous scrubs (<italic>Pegano-Salsoletea</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1510</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean salt steppes (<italic>Limonietalia</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1530</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pannonic salt steppes and salt marshes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1610</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltic esker islands with sandy, rocky and shingle beach vegetation and sublittoral vegetation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1620</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boreal Baltic islets and small islands</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1630*</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boreal Baltic coastal meadows</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1640</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boreal Baltic sandy beaches with perennial vegetation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1650</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boreal Baltic narrow inlets</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>2</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Dune Habitats</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2110</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryonic shifting dunes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2120</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifting dunes along the shoreline with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Ammophila">Ammophila</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="arenaria">arenaria</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (“white dunes”)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2140</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decalcified fixed dunes with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Empetrum">Empetrum</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="nigrum">nigrum</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2150</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atlantic decalcified fixed dunes (<italic>Calluno-Ulicetea</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2160</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunes with <italic>Hippophaë rhamnoides</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2170</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunes with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salix">Salix</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="repens">repens</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> ssp. <italic>argentea</italic> (<italic>Salicion arenariae</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2180</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wooded dunes of the Atlantic, Continental and Boreal region</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2190</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humid dune slacks</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21A0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Machairs (* in Ireland)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2210</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crucianellion maritimae</italic> fixed beach dunes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunes with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Euphorbia">Euphorbia</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="terracina">terracina</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2230</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Malcolmietalia</italic> dune grasslands</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2260</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cisto-Lavenduletalia</italic> dune sclerophyllous scrubs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2270</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wooded dunes with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Pinus">Pinus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="pinea">pinea</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and/or <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Pinus">Pinus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="pinaster">pinaster</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2340</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pannonic inland dunes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>3</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Freshwater habitats</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3110</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligotrophic waters (<italic>Littorelletalia uniflorae</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3120</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligotrophic waters of West Med. with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Isoetes">Isoetes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3130</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligo to mesotrophic waters (<italic>Littorelletea/Isoeto-Nano</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3140</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hard oligo-mesotrophic waters with benthic <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Chara">Chara</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3150</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural euthrophic lakes (<italic>Magnopotamion/ Hydrochachition</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3160</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural dystrophic lakes and ponds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3170</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean temporary ponds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3180</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turloughs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3190</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lakes of gypsum karst</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31A0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transylvanian hot-spring lotus beds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3210</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fennoscandian natural rivers</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpine rivers and herbaceous veg. along their banks</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3230</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpine rivers and ligneous veg. with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Myricaria">Myricaria</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="germanica">germanica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3240</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpine rivers and ligneous vegetation with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salix">Salix</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="eleagnos">eleagnos</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3250</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constantly flowing Med. rivers with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Glaucium">Glaucium</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="flavum">flavum</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3260</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water courses of plain to montane level (<italic>Ranunculion)</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3270</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rivers with muddy banks <italic>(Chenopodion rubri and Bidention)</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3280</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constantly flowing Med. rivers (<italic>Paspalo-Agrostidion</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3290</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermittently flowing Med. rivers (<italic>Paspalo-Agrostidion)</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32A0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tufa cascades of karstic rivers in the Dinaric Alps</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>6</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Grassland Habitats</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6120</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xeric sand calcareous grasslands</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6270</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fennoscandian lowland species-rich dry to mesic grasslands</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6410</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molinia meadows on calcareous, peaty or clayey-silt-laden soils (<italic>Molinion caeruleae)</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6420</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean tall humid grasslands of the <italic>Molinio-Holoschoenion</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6430</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrophilous tall herb fringe communities of plains and of the montane to alpine levels</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6440</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alluvial meadows of river valleys of the <italic>Cnidion dubii</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6450</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northern boreal alluvial meadows</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6460</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peat grasslands of Troodos</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6510</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lowland hay meadows (<italic>Alopecurus pratensis, Sanguisorba officinalis</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6540</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sub-Mediterranean grasslands of the <italic>Molinio-Hordeion secalini</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>7</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Raised bogs and mires and fens</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northern Atlantic wet heaths with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Erica">Erica</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="tetralix">tetralix</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4020</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperate Atlantic wet heaths with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Erica">Erica</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="ciliaris">ciliaris</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Erica">Erica</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="tetralix">tetralix</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5140</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Cistus">Cistus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="palhinhae">palhinhae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> formations on maritime wet heaths</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7110</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active raised bogs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7120</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degraded raised bogs capable of natural regeneration</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7130</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blanket bog (*active only)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7140</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transition mires and quaking bogs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7150</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depressions on peat substrates of the <italic>Rhynchosporion</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7160</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fennoscandian mineral-rich springs and springfens</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7210</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcareous fens with <italic>Cladium mariscus and Caricion davallianae</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petrifying springs with tufa formation (<italic>Cratoneurion</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7230</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaline fens</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7240</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpine pioneer formations (<italic>Caricion bicoloris-atrofuscae)</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7310</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aapa mires</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7320</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palsa mires</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>9</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Forest Habitats</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9030</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural forests of primary succession stages of land upheaval coast</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9080</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fennoscandian deciduous</italic> swamp woods</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9160</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sub-Atlantic and medio-European oak or oak-hornbeam forests of the <italic>Carpinion betuli</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9170</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Galio-Carpinetum</italic> oak-hornbeam forests</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91D0*</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bog woodland</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91E0*</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alluvial forests with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Alnus">Alnus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="glutinosa">glutinosa</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Fraxinus">Fraxinus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="excelsior">excelsior</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>Alno-Padion</italic>, <italic>Alnion incanae</italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salicion">Salicion</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="albae">albae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91F0*</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riparian mixed forests of <italic>Quercus robur, Ulmus laevis</italic> and <italic>Ulmus minor, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Fraxinus">Fraxinus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="excelsior">excelsior</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> or <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Fraxinus">Fraxinus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="angustifolia">angustifolia</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, along the great rivers (<italic>Ulmenion minoris</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92A0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salix">Salix</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="alba">alba</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Populus">Populus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="alba">alba</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies" reg="galleries">galleries</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92B0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riparian formations on intermittent Mediterranean water courses with <italic>Rhododendron ponticum, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Salix">Salix</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and others</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92C0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus" reg="Platanus">Platanus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species" reg="orientalis">orientalis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and Liquidambar orientalis woods (<italic>Platanion orientalis</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92D0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern riparian galleries and thickets (<italic>Nerio-Tamaricetea and Securinegion tinctoriae</italic>)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </app>
    </app-group>
  </back>
</article>
