<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.0/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">183</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="categories">
          <subject>Agricultural Science</subject>
          <subject>Soil Science</subject>
          <subject>Science Policy</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Citations and the <italic>h</italic> index of soil researchers and journals in the Web of Science, Scopus, and Google Scholar</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="authors">
        <contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Minasny</surname>
            <given-names>Budiman</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref>
          <email>budiman.minasny@sydney.edu.au</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hartemink</surname>
            <given-names>Alfred E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McBratney</surname>
            <given-names>Alex</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Ho-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Environmental Sciences, Faculty of Agriculture &amp; Environment, The University of Sydney</institution>, <country>Australia</country>
            </aff>
        <aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Soil Science, FD Hole Soils Lab, University of Wisconsin – Madison</institution>, <addr-line>Madison, WI</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
            </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="editors">
        <contrib id="editor-1" contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2013-10-22">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <elocation-id>e183</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2013-09-09">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2013-10-01">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2013 Minasny et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Minasny et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citation metrics and <italic>h</italic> indices differ using different bibliometric databases. We compiled the number of publications, number of citations, <italic>h</italic> index and year since the first publication from 340 soil researchers from all over the world. On average, Google Scholar has the highest <italic>h</italic> index, number of publications and citations per researcher, and the Web of Science the lowest. The number of papers in Google Scholar is on average 2.3 times higher and the number of citations is 1.9 times higher compared to the data in the Web of Science. Scopus metrics are slightly higher than that of the Web of Science. The <italic>h</italic> index in Google Scholar is on average 1.4 times larger than Web of Science, and the <italic>h</italic> index in Scopus is on average 1.1 times larger than Web of Science. Over time, the metrics increase in all three databases but fastest in Google Scholar. The <italic>h</italic> index of an individual soil scientist is about 0.7 times the number of years since his/her first publication. There is a large difference between the number of citations, number of publications and the <italic>h</italic> index using the three databases. From this analysis it can be concluded that the choice of the database affects widely-used citation and evaluation metrics but that bibliometric transfer functions exist to relate the metrics from these three databases. We also investigated the relationship between journal’s impact factor and Google Scholar’s <italic>h</italic>5-index. The <italic>h</italic>5-index is a better measure of a journal’s citation than the 2 or 5 year window impact factor.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>Soil science</kwd>
        <kwd>Bibliometrics</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>h</italic> index</kwd>
        <kwd>Impact factor</kwd>
        <kwd>Citations</kwd>
        <kwd>Transfer functions</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>There was no funding for this work.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Scientific impact measures are increasingly being used for academic promotions, grant evaluations and evaluation of job vacancy candidates. They are also being used for the evaluations of university departments and research centres. Traditionally, the impact factor of a journal has been used – a metric developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-9">Garfield (1955)</xref> whereby the citations and number of papers published over a given period are divided. For most journals it shows considerable inter-annual fluctuation and it provides no information on individual papers nor individual authors. Since 2005, the <italic>h</italic> index has been used as an index for quantifying the scientific productivity of scientists based on their publication record (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11">Hirsch, 2005</xref>). It is a personal index and provides information on the number of publications of an author and the number of citations: A scholar with an index of <italic>h</italic> has published <italic>h</italic> papers with at least <italic>h</italic> citations each. The <italic>h</italic> index can also be calculated for journals, departments, universities or countries.</p>
      <p>The three widely used bibliometric databases for analysis and evaluations of citations and the <italic>h</italic> index are Web of Science (Thomson Reuters), Scopus (Elsevier), and Google Scholar. Some papers have compared citations between these three databases. Although Google Scholar and Scopus seem to provide higher numbers of citations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-6">Falagas et al., 2008</xref>), there is mixed information on the <italic>h</italic> index. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1">Bar-Ilan (2008)</xref> compared the <italic>h</italic> index for 47 highly-cited Israeli researchers across the three databases and concluded that the results from Google Scholar are considerably different from Web of Science and Scopus. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-20">Mingers &amp; Lipitakis (2010)</xref> looked at 4,600 publications from three UK business schools, and found that Web of Science poorly covers the management discipline compared to Google Scholar. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">De Groote &amp; Raszewski (2012)</xref> examined 31 faculty members from nursing faculty in the Midwestern USA, and concluded that more than one database should be used to calculate the <italic>h</italic> index. They further recommended that since the <italic>h</italic> index rankings differ among databases, comparisons between researchers should be done only within a specified database.</p>
      <p>The difference between the three databases has been fairly well established and the three databases will calculate different citations and <italic>h</italic> indices. As far as we know, the relationships between the three databases have not been investigated and derived. The aims of this paper are therefore: (i) to compare citations and <italic>h</italic> index across the three databases, (ii) to derive transfer functions to convert metrics from one database to the others, and (iii) to compare impact factors for journals and the <italic>h</italic> index. Hereto we have compared the data from 340 researchers and 31 journals. Since we are soil scientists, we have used only soil researchers and journals in this study.</p>
      <p>Soil science is a study of soil as a natural phenomenon and resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3">Brevik &amp; Hartemink, 2010</xref>). It is a relatively small discipline in terms of number of researchers, number of papers per annum, and citations. The IUSS (International Union of Soil Sciences) database lists about 50,000 soil scientists worldwide, but only a fraction of these are in research and actively publish, with a guesstimate of 5,000 to 10,000 publishing researchers. The “soil” topic has lower number of papers and citations when compared to other subjects of natural resources such as “air” and “water” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-18">Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney, 2007</xref>). The number of published papers in 2011 according to Scopus with “soil” in the abstract and keywords is 39,504, with a rate of increase of about 2,000 papers per year. In comparison the number of papers in 2011 on “air” is 1.4 times larger and the number of papers on “water” is 3.5 times larger. The <italic>h</italic> index ratios for water, air, and soil (for the papers published in 2011) are 1.7, 1.3, and 1.0. Nevertheless soil is becoming more important with strong links to global issues of food security, biodiversity, land use change, and climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-15">McBratney, Field &amp; Koch, 2014</xref>). While this study only used soil researchers, the bibliometric results are illustrative to other agricultural, environmental, earth science and biology disciplines, and to small scientific disciplines in general.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Data and Methods</title>
      <p>Google Scholar (GS) is a bibliographic database freely available from Google. It was introduced in 2004 and contains scholarly works across many disciplines and sources, including theses, books, reports, abstracts, peer-reviewed and non-reviewed articles, and web pages that are deemed scholarly. Google Scholar lists these automatically from its search engine activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Harzing &amp; van der Wal, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-23">Vine, 2006</xref>). An individual Google Scholar page was featured in 2012, where a researcher can create a webpage, with fields of interest. Google Scholar automatically searches and populates the individual’s publications, calculates and displays the individual’s total number of citations, <italic>h</italic> index, and i10 index. Scopus, or SciVerse Scopus, is a bibliographic database from Elsevier which contains abstracts and citations for academic journal articles, conference papers, and book chapters. Inclusion in the database is through the Scopus Content Selection and Advisory Board. Although its record goes back as early as 1823, its citations are reliable after 1995. The Web of Science is a bibliographic database from Thompson Reuters which only contained abstracts and citations for articles listed in the Web of Science indexed journals since 1900 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Harzing &amp; van der Wal, 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>Data from researchers who listed their areas of interest as: “soil science”, “soil”, “pedology”, “soil physics”, “soil biology”, “soil chemistry”, “soil fertility”, “soil erosion”, “soil ecology”, and “soil carbon” were retrieved from the Google Scholar author pages. The same researchers were located in Scopus and the Web of Science. In Scopus, the ‘Author Identifier’ tool was used to locate the researcher. In the Web of Science, the author’s surname and first name’s initial was used, together with “soil” in the search subject. When the name and publication record were inconsistent across all three databases, the researcher was not included in our analysis. At the end, we collected data from 340 researchers and this included: number of total citations, <italic>h</italic> index, number of papers, and year of the first publication. These data were obtained for each researcher and from each of the three databases. The publications and citations are until June 2013.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Number of papers, citations and <italic>h</italic> index</title>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref> shows the statistics of <italic>h</italic> index, number of publications, number of citations, and year of the first paper for 340 soil researchers in the three databases. Our data encompass a wide range of researchers from early-career to well-established and highly-cited researchers. The database is much larger and more diverse than previous studies where a small and focussed group of researchers was used to compare citation metrics between the databases (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-7">Franceschet, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-17">Meho &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">Patel et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-1">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-1</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Descriptive statistics of publication indices from Google Scholar, Scopus and Web of Science database for 340 soil researchers.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-1.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left"/>
                  <th align="left">Number of<break/>citations</th>
                  <th align="left">Number of<break/>papers</th>
                  <th align="left">First year of<break/>publication</th>
                  <th align="left"><italic>h</italic> index</th>
                  <th align="left"><italic>m</italic> (rate of <italic>h</italic> index<break/>increase per year)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Google Scholar</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Minimum</td>
                  <td align="left">16</td>
                  <td align="left">3</td>
                  <td align="left">1953</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">0.09</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">25th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">266</td>
                  <td align="left">32</td>
                  <td align="left">1985</td>
                  <td align="left">26</td>
                  <td align="left">0.56</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Median</td>
                  <td align="left">866</td>
                  <td align="left">79</td>
                  <td align="left">1993</td>
                  <td align="left">15</td>
                  <td align="left">0.85</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">75th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">2596</td>
                  <td align="left">146</td>
                  <td align="left">2001</td>
                  <td align="left">26</td>
                  <td align="left">1.18</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Maximum</td>
                  <td align="left">49447</td>
                  <td align="left">1159</td>
                  <td align="left">2011</td>
                  <td align="left">115</td>
                  <td align="left">3.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Scopus</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Minimum</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">1955</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">0.03</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">25th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">116</td>
                  <td align="left">14</td>
                  <td align="left">1989</td>
                  <td align="left">5</td>
                  <td align="left">0.45</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Median</td>
                  <td align="left">469</td>
                  <td align="left">34</td>
                  <td align="left">1996</td>
                  <td align="left">11</td>
                  <td align="left">0.71</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">75th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">1361</td>
                  <td align="left">65</td>
                  <td align="left">2004</td>
                  <td align="left">19</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Maximum</td>
                  <td align="left">28693</td>
                  <td align="left">423</td>
                  <td align="left">2011</td>
                  <td align="left">70</td>
                  <td align="left">2.87</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Web of Science</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Minimum</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">1957</td>
                  <td align="left">1</td>
                  <td align="left">0.06</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">25th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">76</td>
                  <td align="left">10</td>
                  <td align="left">1991</td>
                  <td align="left">5</td>
                  <td align="left">0.41</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Median</td>
                  <td align="left">291</td>
                  <td align="left">23</td>
                  <td align="left">1998</td>
                  <td align="left">10</td>
                  <td align="left">0.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">75th Quantile</td>
                  <td align="left">945</td>
                  <td align="left">48</td>
                  <td align="left">2004</td>
                  <td align="left">17</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Maximum</td>
                  <td align="left">32837</td>
                  <td align="left">424</td>
                  <td align="left">2011</td>
                  <td align="left">96</td>
                  <td align="left">2.87</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The median number of papers for the 340 soil researchers ranged from 23 (Web of Science) to 79 (Google Scholar) with Scopus having intermediate values. The number of citations is also highest in Google scholar, with a median of 866 citations per author whereas it is 291 in the Web of Science. The <italic>h</italic> index and its annual increase are lowest in the Web of Science. This pattern holds for all of the metrics presented here: Google Scholar has the highest numbers and the Web of Science the lowest whereas the Scopus numbers are in between. Part of this may be the different types of publications included and also the periods of time covered by the 3 databases are slightly different.</p>
        <p>A simple linear regression without intercept was performed between the citation indices of the three databases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2</xref>). Google Scholar has on average 2.3 times more articles and 1.9 times more citations than the Web of Science. The Scopus database (all years) has 1.1 times more papers than the Web of Science but a similar number of citations compared to the Web of Science. Since the citations are more correct and complete after 1995, a revision was made to the relationship for post 1995 authors; it shows that Scopus has about 1.2 times more citations than the Web of Science. The 20% higher citations are consistent with the findings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-6">Falagas et al. (2008)</xref> in the field of medicine. Similarly, for articles in medical journals, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-13">Kulkarni et al. (2009)</xref> found that Google Scholar and Scopus retrieved more citations compared to Web of Science (1.22 and 1.20 times respectively).</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-2">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-2</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of publication indices from Google Scholar (GS), Scopus and Web of Science (WoS).</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-2.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left"/>
                  <th align="left">Standard error <break/>of estimates</th>
                  <th align="left">
                    <italic>R</italic>
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS no. papers = 2.33 WoS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left">0.797</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS no. citations = 1.87 WoS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.05</td>
                  <td align="left">0.809</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS <italic>h</italic> index = 1.44 WoS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.956</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. papers = 1.09 WoS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.902</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. citations = 1.03 WoS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.867</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus <italic>h</italic> index = 0.99 WoS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left">0.936</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Authors who started to publish after 1995</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. papers = 1.11 WoS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.03</td>
                  <td align="left">0.900</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. citations = 1.17 WoS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.949</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus <italic>h</italic> index = 1.11 WoS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.954</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="fig-1">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-1</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relationship between the number of papers, the number of citations, and the <italic>h</italic> index of 340 soil researchers in the Web of Science (WoS), Scopus and Google Scholar (GS).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-1.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The relationship between number of papers and citations is scattered, especially for the number of papers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>), but the relationships between <italic>h</italic> index values across the 3 databases appear to be quite linear. The <italic>h</italic> index in Google Scholar is on average 1.4 times larger than Web of Science, and the <italic>h</italic> index in Scopus (post 1995 authors) is on average 1.1 times larger than Web of Science. However, for pre-1995 authors, their Scopus <italic>h</italic> index is similar and sometimes can be smaller when compared to Web of Science. While Google Scholar contains more grey literature (informally published written material) and its citations may contain errors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Harzing &amp; van der Wal, 2009</xref>), the <italic>h</italic> index appears to be quite robust and comparable with Web of Science and Scopus. This is due to the fact that <italic>h</italic> index does not vary greatly if the number of articles increases (e.g., book chapters or unrefereed articles). In addition, extra citations do not have a large effect on the <italic>h</italic> index, as once a paper has reached <italic>h</italic> citations additional citations to that paper do not affect its value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-8">Franceschini, Maisano &amp; Mastrogiacomo, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4">Courtault &amp; Hayek, 2008</xref>).</p>
        <p>Our results are different from the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-7">Franceschet (2010)</xref> who evaluated 13 computer scientists from his university’s department and found that on average Google Scholar had five times more papers, eight times more citations and a three-fold larger <italic>h</italic> index. Our results from 340 soil researchers are more in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">De Groote &amp; Raszewski (2012)</xref> who looked at 30 researchers from nursing and found that the <italic>h</italic> index from Google Scholar is 1.3 times larger than the Web of Science, and Scopus is 1.1 times larger than the <italic>h</italic> index in the Web of Science. Similar results were obtained by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-17">Meho &amp; Rogers (2008)</xref> who evaluated 22 human–computer interaction researchers from the UK and found that the <italic>h</italic> index in Google Scholar is on average 1.6 times higher than Web of Science. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">Patel et al. (2013)</xref> compared publications and citations for 195 Nobel Laureates in Physiology and Medicine using the three databases. They found no concordance between the three databases when considering the number of publications and citations count per Laureate. However, the <italic>h</italic> index was the most reliably calculated bibliometric index across the three databases.</p>
        <p>We calculated the Spearman’s rank correlation (ρ) of the <italic>h</italic> index of the 340 researchers from the three databases. The three databases show excellent correlation for the <italic>h</italic> index, with WoS and GS as having the largest concordance. Unexpectedly, the rank correlation in terms of no. citations and no. papers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-3">Table 3</xref>) also indicates that the three databases are comparable. This implies that the ranking of individuals within a database is comparable with the other databases. Our correlation is also much higher compared to the 13 computer scientists studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-7">Franceschet (2010)</xref> who only obtained ρ = 0.65. We used a much larger dataset, and the GS data came from the page that was created by the researcher, thus the listed papers and citations are assumed to be more complete.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-3">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-3</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient (ρ) of the <italic>h</italic> index of the 340 researchers using Google Scholar (GS), Scopus and Web of Science (WoS).</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-3.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">Variable</th>
                  <th align="left">By variable</th>
                  <th align="left">Spearman ρ</th>
                  <th align="left">Prob &gt; |ρ|</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">GS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.939</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">GS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.931</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">Scopus <italic>h</italic> index</td>
                  <td align="left">0.922</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">GS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.939</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">GS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.955</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. citations</td>
                  <td align="left">0.945</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">GS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.840</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">GS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.896</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. papers</td>
                  <td align="left">0.905</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The <italic>h</italic> index of soil researchers</title>
        <p>In an earlier paper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-18">Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney, 2007</xref>) we investigated the relationship between the <italic>h</italic> index of 228 soil researchers and found that the index was 0.7 times the number of years since the first publication (which we called scientific age, or <italic>t</italic>). That means if a researcher has been publishing for 10 years his/her <italic>h</italic> index should be about 7. We calculated this index using the Web of Science database, and now we repeated this using analysis to the 340 soil researchers in this study (which are different from the previous list) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Although the data are scattered the relationship holds: <disp-formula id="eqn-1">
                  <alternatives><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/eqn-1.png"/><tex-math id="tex-eqn-1"><![CDATA[\begin{eqnarray*} \displaystyle h\text{ index}=0.73\times \text{ scientific age}\quad ({R}^{2}=0.72).&&\displaystyle \end{eqnarray*}]]></tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn-1"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mtext> index</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>73</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mtext> scientific age</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="1em" class="quad"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>72</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></alternatives>
               </disp-formula> The Web of Science database shows that the average rate of <italic>h</italic> index increase over time (<italic>m</italic>) is 0.7, with the lowest value of 0.06 and highest value of 2.9 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>). The average <italic>m</italic> value for Scopus is 0.7 and for Google Scholar it is 0.8 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig-2">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-2</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relationship between the scientific age (<italic>t</italic>) of 340 soil researchers and the <italic>h</italic> index (Web of Science data).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-2.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-16">McCarty &amp; Jawitz (2013)</xref> evaluated the linear relationship between scientific age and <italic>h</italic> index for 4 disciplines and found the following mean <italic>m</italic> values of 0.83, 0.47, 0.43, and 0.36 for biochemistry, water, economics, and anthropology, respectively. Thus the trend of soil science is in between water and biochemistry.</p>
        <p>For selected researchers, we tried to calculate the distribution of <italic>m</italic> (<italic>h</italic> index divided by the number of years since first publication) as a function of sub-disciplines in soil science. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-5">Table 5</xref> shows the distribution of <italic>m</italic> for WoS and GS according to 6 sub-disciplines. It shows that <italic>h</italic> index varies between sub-diciplines, for WoS, soil biology, biogeochemistry and ecology have the highest <italic>m</italic> values (median of 0.8). This is followed by soil physics, soil fertility and management, soil geography and pedometrics, chemistry and lastly pedology (average <italic>m</italic> = 0.5). The order in Google Scholar is slightly different, but it is consistent in that soil biology has the highest <italic>m</italic> value and pedology is the lowest. Therefore within soil science, the sub-disciplines also vary in terms of <italic>h</italic> index. The citation ratios are: Soil biology, ecology and biogeochemistry, Soil management and fertility, Soil geography &amp; pedometrics, Soil physics, Soil chemistry and mineralogy, Pedology 1: 0.9: 0.8: 0.8: 0.8: 0.6; respectively.</p>
        <p>Although the number of citations for researchers across the three databases can be quite different, the relationship between the number of citations and the <italic>h</italic> index is quite consistent across the three databases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>): <disp-formula id="eqn-2">
                  <alternatives><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/eqn-2.png"/><tex-math id="tex-eqn-2"><![CDATA[\begin{eqnarray*} \displaystyle h\text{ index}=\unicode{x00BD} {n}^{\unicode{x00BD} }\quad ({R}^{2}=0.95).&&\displaystyle \end{eqnarray*}]]></tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn-2"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mtext> index</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>½</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>½</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="1em" class="quad"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></alternatives>
               </disp-formula> This relationship follows the function postulated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11">Hirsch (2005)</xref> where the number of citations is about 3 to 5 times <italic>h</italic><sup>2</sup>, and it appears the <italic>h</italic> index follows an absorption-type relationship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-24">Warrick, 2003</xref>), increasing rapidly at low numbers of citations with the rate decreasing with increasing number of citations.</p>
        <fig id="fig-3">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-3</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relationship between the number of citations and the <italic>h</italic> index of 340 soil researchers from 3 databases.</title>
            <p>Black dots are data from Web of Science, green squares are from Scopus, and blue triangles are from Google Scholar.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-3.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table 4</xref> shows the relationship of the average number of papers and citations per year for the 340 soil researchers. This can be interpreted as: on average, a soil researcher produces 5 articles per year, 2 articles in international refereed journals, 1 in a conference proceedings, and 2 other unrefereed publications. The researcher receives 65 citations per year from journal articles, an additional 13 citations from conference proceedings and another 44 citations from other publications.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-4">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-4</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of the <italic>h</italic> index over time using the data from 340 soil researchers in Google Scholar (GS), Scopus and Web of Science (WoS).</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-4.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left"/>
                  <th align="left">Standard error of<break/>estimates</th>
                  <th align="left">
                    <italic>R</italic>
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS <italic>h</italic> index = 0.84 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.745</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS <italic>h</italic> index = 0.73 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.717</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus <italic>h</italic> index = 0.73 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left">0.759</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS no. papers = 5.5 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.23</td>
                  <td align="left">0.620</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. papers = 2.5 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.12</td>
                  <td align="left">0.567</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. papers = 3.0 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">0.12</td>
                  <td align="left">0.656</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">GS no. citations = 122 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">9.1</td>
                  <td align="left">0.344</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">WoS no. citations = 65 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">5.8</td>
                  <td align="left">0.269</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Scopus no. citations = 78 × year</td>
                  <td align="left">5.8</td>
                  <td align="left">0.346</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Self-citations</title>
        <p>A way to boost the <italic>h</italic> index is by self-citation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-12">Hyland (2003)</xref> found that self-citation is 12% of all references in biology, engineering and physics, compared to 4% in sociology, philosophy, linguistics, or marketing. For soil science journals, we found a mean of 12% self-citations but it differs between the sub-disciplines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney, 2010</xref>). High rates of self-citation were accompanied by high journal impact factor ranking; China and the USA had the highest rates of self-citation whereas Egypt, Algeria, Ukraine, and Indonesia have low levels of self-citations in soil science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney, 2010</xref>).</p>
        <p>So high rates of self-citation may influence the <italic>h</italic> index and the Scopus database allows calculation of the <italic>h</italic> index with and without self-citation. Self-citation here is the so-called diachronous kind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-14">Lawani, 1982</xref>), which is self-citation from the citations received by the author. The other type is called synchronous which is more difficult to calculate, i.e., author’s self-referencing relative to the total number of references cited in a paper.</p>
        <p>The relationship for the 340 soil researchers is consistent and the average <italic>h</italic> index without self-citation is about 12% lower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>): <disp-formula id="eqn-3">
                  <alternatives><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/eqn-3.png"/><tex-math id="tex-eqn-3"><![CDATA[\begin{eqnarray*} \displaystyle h\text{ index without self-citation}=0.88\times h\text{ index }({R}^{2}=0.97).&&\displaystyle \end{eqnarray*}]]></tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn-3"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mtext> index without self-citation</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>88</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mtext> index </mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>97</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></alternatives>
               </disp-formula>
            </p>
        <fig id="fig-4">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-4</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>(A) Relationship between the <italic>h</italic> index with and without self-citation, (B) relationship between the scientific age of 340 soil researchers and percentage self-citation based on Scopus data.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-4.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We found a weak relationship between percentage of self-citation and scientific age (<italic>t</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>). It suggests that some younger authors appear to have high rates of self citation as their works were not known widely and their citations mainly come from themselves, as the researchers mature their papers are more widely known and more external citations were gained thus a lower percentage of self-citations: <disp-formula id="eqn-4">
                  <alternatives><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/eqn-4.png"/><tex-math id="tex-eqn-4"><![CDATA[\begin{eqnarray*} \displaystyle \text{Percent self-citation}=42-5{t}^{0.5}\quad ({R}^{2}=0.18).&&\displaystyle \end{eqnarray*}]]></tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn-4"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtext>Percent self-citation</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="1em" class="quad"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></alternatives>
               </disp-formula>
            </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Journal citations</title>
        <p>We retrieved 31 Soil Science journal impact factors (IF) and other metrics from the 2012 Thompson Reuters Journal Citation Reports (JCR, released in June 2013). Google Scholar also has measures of the journal’s metric, the <italic>h</italic>5-index, which is the <italic>h</italic> index for articles published in that journal for the last five years. The list of journals for the soil science discipline in Google Scholar is slightly different from the Thompson Reuters Journal Citation Reports (JCR), and therefore we used the journals listed in JCR as the basis for comparison. We searched for the <italic>h</italic>5-index for the journals in Google Scholar metrics for 2012 (released July 2013).</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-5">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-5</object-id>
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The distribution of <italic>m</italic> (<italic>h</italic> index divided by the number of years since first publication) according to sub-disciplines in soil science using the data from Google Scholar, Scopus and Web of Science, <italic>n</italic> is the number of samples, Q25 and Q75 refers to the lower and upper quartile.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-5.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left"/>
                  <th align="left">
                    <italic>n</italic>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left">Min</th>
                  <th align="left">Q25</th>
                  <th align="left">Median</th>
                  <th align="left">Q75</th>
                  <th align="left">Max</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Google Scholar</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Pedology</td>
                  <td align="left">25</td>
                  <td align="left">0.09</td>
                  <td align="left">0.37</td>
                  <td align="left">0.56</td>
                  <td align="left">0.83</td>
                  <td align="left">1.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil chemistry</td>
                  <td align="left">42</td>
                  <td align="left">0.09</td>
                  <td align="left">0.45</td>
                  <td align="left">0.78</td>
                  <td align="left">1.16</td>
                  <td align="left">2.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil physics</td>
                  <td align="left">67</td>
                  <td align="left">0.21</td>
                  <td align="left">0.56</td>
                  <td align="left">0.79</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                  <td align="left">2.55</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil geography &amp; pedometrics</td>
                  <td align="left">28</td>
                  <td align="left">0.16</td>
                  <td align="left">0.58</td>
                  <td align="left">0.87</td>
                  <td align="left">1.02</td>
                  <td align="left">1.93</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil management &amp; fertility</td>
                  <td align="left">42</td>
                  <td align="left">0.28</td>
                  <td align="left">0.69</td>
                  <td align="left">0.98</td>
                  <td align="left">1.30</td>
                  <td align="left">2.12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil biology, ecology, biogeochemistry</td>
                  <td align="left">88</td>
                  <td align="left">0.23</td>
                  <td align="left">0.78</td>
                  <td align="left">1.01</td>
                  <td align="left">1.65</td>
                  <td align="left">3.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">
                              <bold>Web of Science</bold>
                           </td>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                  <td align="left"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Pedology</td>
                  <td align="left">25</td>
                  <td align="left">0.08</td>
                  <td align="left">0.32</td>
                  <td align="left">0.46</td>
                  <td align="left">0.78</td>
                  <td align="left">1.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil chemistry</td>
                  <td align="left">42</td>
                  <td align="left">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left">0.32</td>
                  <td align="left">0.63</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                  <td align="left">1.67</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil geography &amp; pedometrics</td>
                  <td align="left">67</td>
                  <td align="left">0.11</td>
                  <td align="left">0.50</td>
                  <td align="left">0.64</td>
                  <td align="left">0.86</td>
                  <td align="left">1.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil management &amp; fertility</td>
                  <td align="left">28</td>
                  <td align="left">0.15</td>
                  <td align="left">0.47</td>
                  <td align="left">0.67</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                  <td align="left">1.63</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil physics</td>
                  <td align="left">42</td>
                  <td align="left">0.17</td>
                  <td align="left">0.46</td>
                  <td align="left">0.72</td>
                  <td align="left">1.00</td>
                  <td align="left">2.14</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">Soil biology, ecology, biogeochemistry</td>
                  <td align="left">88</td>
                  <td align="left">0.14</td>
                  <td align="left">0.63</td>
                  <td align="left">0.83</td>
                  <td align="left">1.33</td>
                  <td align="left">2.87</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="table-6">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/table-6</object-id>
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient (ρ) of the Google Scholar <italic>h</italic>5-index and impact factor (IF), no. papers, citations, and Eigenfactor metrics from Journal Citation Reports for 31 soil science journals. Cites is the number of citations in 2012 for papers that were published in 2007–2011.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/table-6.png"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
                <col align="left"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">Variable</th>
                  <th align="left">By variable</th>
                  <th align="left">Spearman ρ</th>
                  <th align="left">Prob &gt; |ρ|</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left"><italic>h</italic>5-index</td>
                  <td align="left">Cites (5 years)</td>
                  <td align="left">0.972</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left"><italic>h</italic>5-index</td>
                  <td align="left">Eigenfactor</td>
                  <td align="left">0.970</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left"><italic>h</italic>5-index</td>
                  <td align="left">5 year IF</td>
                  <td align="left">0.903</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left"><italic>h</italic>5-index</td>
                  <td align="left">2 year IF</td>
                  <td align="left">0.870</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left"><italic>h</italic>5-index</td>
                  <td align="left">No. papers (5 years)</td>
                  <td align="left">0.721</td>
                  <td align="left">&lt;.0001</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-6">Table 6</xref> shows that Google Scholar <italic>h</italic>5-index has a better correlation with the five year IF (impact factor) than the two year IF, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref> shows the comparison between GS <italic>h</italic>5-index and the five year IF. While the <italic>h</italic>5-index and five year IF have a high rank correlation (ρ = 0.90), the ranking is different for different journals. The journals ‘Soil Biology and Biochemistry’ and ‘Plant and Soil’ both consistently ranked no. 1 and 2 in JCR and GS while other journals appear to be slightly different in their ranking (1 to 3 places difference). The top two journals are able to maintain a large number of citations relative to the number of papers they publish.</p>
        <fig id="fig-5">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-5</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>A comparison between 5 year Impact factor (IF) and Google Scholar <italic>h</italic>5-index for 31 soil science journals in 2012.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-5.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>There are 4 journals that are ranked much higher ( &gt;  =  4 difference in rank) in Google Scholar compared to the IF: ‘Soil Science Society of America Journal’, ‘Journal of Plant Nutrition and Soil Science’, ‘Pedosphere’, and ‘Revista Brasileira de Ciência do Solo’. All these journals are published by national soil science societies (USA, Germany, China and Brazil). In the case of ‘Revista Brasileira de Ciência do Solo’ which ranked 12 in GS and 25 in JCR, Google Scholar includes more citations from non-English articles. Contrarily, there are four journals that are ranked much lower ( &lt;  =  4 difference in rank) in Google Scholar: ‘European Journal of Soil Science’, ‘Soil Use and Management’, ‘Journal of Soil and Water Conservation’, and ‘Soil Science’.</p>
        <p>The Thompson Reuters Journal Citation Reports suffers from a miscalculation, for example, ‘Australian Journal of Soil Research’ was reported to have a 2 year IF of 3.443. This is a miscalculation, as the journal changed its name to ‘Soil Research’ in 2011, and the IF calculation for Australian Journal of Soil Research only accounts for papers published until 2010. ‘Soil Research’ was again listed as a separate journal in JCR. We have recalculated the actual impact factor for this journal in our analysis.</p>
        <p>While there is a positive correlation between cites (citations in 2012 to papers published from the previous 5 years) and IF, we can see that there are 2 trends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6A</xref>). For journals that published &lt;700 papers between 2007 and 2011 (or on average less than 140 papers per year) IF tends to increase rapidly with increasing citations (1.2 increase in IF per 1000 citations). For the other 7 journals that published more than 700 papers, the slope is half as much (0.6 IF increase per 1000 citations). So there is a drawback for journals that publish more papers. Meanwhile the <italic>h</italic>5-index is mostly controlled by number of citations following an absorption relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Although the citations come from WoS, the <italic>h</italic>5-index still holds the square-root relationship supporting its robustness.</p>
        <fig id="fig-6">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/fig-6</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>(A) Relationship between cites and 5 year Impact factor (IF), and (B) relationship between cites and Google Scholar <italic>h</italic>5-index for soil science journals in 2012. Cites is the number of citations in 2012 for papers that were published in 2007–2011.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/fig-6.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-6">Table 6</xref> also shows that the GS <italic>h</italic>5-index is more correlated to the Eigenfactor metric compared to IF. The Eigenfactor metric is based on the Google PageRank algorithm which calculated the “influence” of the journal based on the citations weighted by the “quality” of the journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2">Bergstrom, 2007</xref>). A citation from a highly cited journal will have a higher weighting than a lower cited journal. We showed that this metric is less vulnerable to self-citation than the impact factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney, 2010</xref>). Interestingly, Google Scholar does not apply its PageRank for citations.</p>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-22">Vanclay (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4">Courtault &amp; Hayek (2008)</xref>  established that the <italic>h</italic> index is robust and is relatively unaffected by grey literature and errors in citations such as in Google Scholar. Most of the errors (and distortions) in citation databases are found in the ‘long tails’ of the citation distribution and they tend not to affect the <italic>h</italic> index much. For the journals considered here, we calculated the ratio between <italic>h</italic>5-index and number of papers, and it shows that only 1–9% (median 5%) of the total papers that contributed to <italic>h</italic>5-index. In other words, less than 10% of the cited papers are influencing the <italic>h</italic>5-index. We also demonstrated that the <italic>h</italic>5-index keeps its relationship even when using WoS citations.</p>
        <p>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Harzing &amp; van der Wal (2009)</xref> recommended the use of the GS <italic>h</italic> index for Management and International Business journals. We also concur that the <italic>h</italic>5-index is a better measure of a journal’s citation performance than the impact factor as it is more robust and less affected by citation manipulation. It is now acknowledged that there are ways of manipulating impact factor, which include self-citation, and editorials that listed references to previously published articles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-6">Falagas et al., 2008</xref>). The <italic>h</italic> index is less sensitive to the increase in number of citations, while individual highly cited papers can artificially increase the impact factor. In addition, it only considers the top influential <italic>h</italic> papers in the journal, thus it does not penalise a journal for publishing a larger number of papers. Although <italic>h</italic> index can also be manipulated by self-citation, in order to increase the <italic>h</italic> index considerably, a journal has to be more tactical by increasing a significant number of citations to certain papers.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>From this analysis the following can be concluded:</p>
      <list id="list-1" list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>There is a large difference between the number of citations, number of publications and the <italic>h</italic> index using the three different databases.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>On average, Google Scholar gives the largest number of publications, largest number of citations and the highest <italic>h</italic> index. The Web of Science gives the lowest averages.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>There are solid relationships between the <italic>h</italic> indices in these three databases.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>The <italic>h</italic>5-index has a correlation with the five year impact factor, but it is more robust and less affected by citation manipulation. It should be considered as an alternative to the journal’s impact factor.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>This analysis has shown that the choice of the database affects the assessment of scientific impact for academic promotions, grant evaluations, job vacancy candidates or the evaluations of university departments and research centres. It is recommended that we should quote these bibliometric indices for all three databases as they reflect different types of publications. Web of Science uses mostly refereed journal articles, Scopus includes conference proceedings and book chapters, whereas Google Scholar includes other publications (including software). The established relationships between the databases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2</xref>) can be used as bibliometric transfer functions by anyone interested in relating databases. We are not aware of whether these functions have been established for other scientific disciplines but assume they will be similar. As a test, we applied our function relating the <italic>h</italic> index of WoS and GS to the 30 nursing faculty data of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">De Groote &amp; Raszewski (2012)</xref>  and the function gives a good prediction with a Spearman rank correlation of 0.852. We envisage that these functions would work better for science than socio-economical disciplines. However, this needs to be investigated.</p>
      <p>Although we focussed on the relatively small discipline of soil science, the reported researchers has a lot of cross-over with other disciplines, in particular earth science, agricultural science, biogeochemistry and ecology. Many researchers in ecology and microbiology work with soil as a medium, while they do not necessarily study soil as a natural body. Their contributions elevated the citations as compared to pure soil research. The trend of <italic>h</italic> index for soil researchers appears to be in between the water and biochemistry disciplines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-16">McCarty &amp; Jawitz, 2013</xref>). However, soil science publication rate (on average 2.5 papers per year per researcher) is lower compared to water and biochemistry (on average of 3.1 and 3.8 papers per year, respectively).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information">
      <title>Supplemental Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="supp-1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/183/data.xlsx">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.183/supp-1</object-id>
        <label>Supplemental Information 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Bibliometric datasets of researchers and journals used in this study</title>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="additional-information">
      <title>Additional Information and Declarations</title>
      <fn-group content-type="competing-interests">
        <title>Competing Interests</title>
        <fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="con">
          <p>Budiman Minasny is an Academic Editor for PeerJ.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <fn-group content-type="author-contributions">
        <title>Author Contributions</title>
        <fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con">
          <p>
               <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Budiman Minasny</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con">
          <p>
               <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Alfred E. Hartemink</xref> and <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Alex McBratney</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, wrote the paper.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con">
          <p>
               <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Ho-Jun Jang</xref> performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </sec>
    <ref-list content-type="authoryear">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref-1">
        <label>Bar-Ilan (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Bar-Ilan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Which h-index?—A comparison of WoS, Scopus and Google Scholar</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>271</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-008-0216-y</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-2">
        <label>Bergstrom (2007)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Eigenfactor: measuring the value and prestige of scholarly journals</article-title>
          <source>College &amp; Research Libraries News</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>314</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-3">
        <label>Brevik &amp; Hartemink (2010)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Brevik</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Hartemink</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Early soil knowledge and the birth and development of soil science</article-title>
          <source>Catena</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.catena.2010.06.011</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-4">
        <label>Courtault &amp; Hayek (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Courtault</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Hayek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>On the robustness of the h-index: a mathematical approach</article-title>
          <source>Economics Bulletin</source>
          <issue>78</issue>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-5">
        <label>De Groote &amp; Raszewski (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>De Groote</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Raszewski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Coverage of Google Scholar, Scopus, and Web of Science: a case study of the <italic>h</italic>-index in nursing</article-title>
          <source>Nursing Outlook</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>391</fpage>
          <lpage>401</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.outlook.2012.04.007</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-6">
        <label>Falagas et al. (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Pitsouni</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Malietzis</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science, and Google Scholar: strengths and weaknesses</article-title>
          <source>The FASEB Journal</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>338</fpage>
          <lpage>342</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.07-9492LSF</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-7">
        <label>Franceschet (2010)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Franceschet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>A comparison of bibliometric indicators for computer science scholars and journals on Web of Science and Google Scholar</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>258</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-009-0021-2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-8">
        <label>Franceschini, Maisano &amp; Mastrogiacomo (2013)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Maisano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Mastrogiacomo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of database dirty data on <italic>h</italic>-index calculation</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-012-0871-x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-9">
        <label>Garfield (1955)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Garfield</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Citation indexes to science: a new dimension in documentation through association of ideas</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1955">1955</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>108</fpage>
          <lpage>111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.122.3159.108</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-10">
        <label>Harzing &amp; van der Wal (2009)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Harzing</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>van der Wal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>A Google Scholar <italic>h</italic>-index for journals: an alternative metric to measure journal impact in economics and business</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.20953</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-11">
        <label>Hirsch (2005)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>An index to quantify an individual’s scientific research output</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>16569</fpage>
          <lpage>16571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0507655102</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-12">
        <label>Hyland (2003)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Self-citation and self-reference: credibility and promotion in academic publication</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.10204</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-13">
        <label>Kulkarni et al. (2009)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparisons of citations in Web of Science, Scopus, and Google Scholar for articles published in general medical journals</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
          <volume>302</volume>
          <fpage>1092</fpage>
          <lpage>1096</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2009.1307</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-14">
        <label>Lawani (1982)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Lawani</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>On the heterogeneity and classification of author self-citations</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Society for Information Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>284</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.4630330506</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-15">
        <label>McBratney, Field &amp; Koch (2014)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>McBratney</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>The dimensions of soil security</article-title>
          <source>Geoderma</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
          <volume>213</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2013.08.013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-16">
        <label>McCarty &amp; Jawitz (2013)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Jawitz</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Attitudes about publishing and normal science advancement</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Infometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>850</fpage>
          <lpage>858</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joi.2013.08.001</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-17">
        <label>Meho &amp; Rogers (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Meho</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Citation counting, citation ranking, and <italic>h</italic>-index of human–computer interaction researchers: a comparison of Scopus and Web of Science</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1711</fpage>
          <lpage>1726</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.20874</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-18">
        <label>Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney (2007)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Minasny</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Hartemink</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>McBratney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Soil science and the <italic>h</italic> index</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-007-1811-z</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-19">
        <label>Minasny, Hartemink &amp; McBratney (2010)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Minasny</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Hartemink</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>McBratney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Individual, country, and journal self-citation in soil science</article-title>
          <source>Geoderma</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <fpage>434</fpage>
          <lpage>438</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2009.12.003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-20">
        <label>Mingers &amp; Lipitakis (2010)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Mingers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Lipitakis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Counting the citations: a comparison of web of science and google scholar in the field of business and management</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>613</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-010-0270-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-21">
        <label>Patel et al. (2013)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Ashrafian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Almoudaris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Makanjuola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Bucciarelli-Ducci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Darzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
                  <name><surname>Athanasiou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Measuring academic performance for healthcare researchers with the <italic>h</italic> index: which search tool should be used?</article-title>
          <source>Medical Principles and Practice</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>178</fpage>
          <lpage>183</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000341756</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-22">
        <label>Vanclay (2007)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Vanclay</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>On the robustness of the <italic>h</italic>-index</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>1547</fpage>
          <lpage>1550</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.20616</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-23">
        <label>Vine (2006)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Vine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <article-title>Google Scholar. Electronic resources review</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Medical Library Association</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-24">
        <label>Warrick (2003)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name><surname>Warrick</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
               </person-group>
          <source>Soil water dynamics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
